<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sixe-folde politician Together with a sixe-folde precept of policy.</title>
            <author>Melton, John, Sir, d. 1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 129 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112610</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847857</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07419)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 966:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sixe-folde politician Together with a sixe-folde precept of policy.</title>
                  <author>Melton, John, Sir, d. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 174, [2], 117-180, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[dward] A[llde] for Iohn Busby, and are to be solde at his shop in Saint Dunstans Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: I.M., i.e. Sir John Melton.</note>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to John Milton (1563-1647), the poet's father.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:1"/>
            <p>A SIXE-FOLDE <hi>Politician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Sixe-folde Precept of <hi>Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by E. A. for Iohn Busby, and are to be ſolde at his Shop in Saint Dunſtans Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:2"/>
            <head>PHILODESPOTVS <hi>to his</hi> Naear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ouing and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Naearchus, being ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earneſtly ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by you, to ſette downe a patterne of ſuch diſcourſes, as in priuate haue paſt many times betwixt vs, concerning ſeuerall and diſtinct affectes, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectations of many vſurping vaine-glorious Politicians, as alſo what my
<pb facs="tcp:12920:3"/>conceipt and opinion was, and is of a perfect ſtateſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt to be reſpected: And at this time finding my ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued through ſicknes of other bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly functions, I haue endeuoured to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your requeſt, ſo well as the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incomberance of ſo vnwelcome and trouble ſome a gueſt, would giue mee leaue and leaſure; What I haue ſette downe will aſsuredlye offend no creature that liues within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of right &amp; perfect iudgement: and if any thing heerein may giue you the least taſte of pleaſure and content, I ſhall think my trauell ritchly rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and be incouraged to ſupplye your deſires in the like ſucceeding moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Euer vnder the arreſt of your commaund. I. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:3"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Hrine</hi> a Harlot, at a publique feaſt where many Ladies and Gentlemen were aſſembled, vncouering her painted face, tooke warm water and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off her <hi>Fucus</hi> wiſhing all other Ladies there preſent to imitate her plainneſſe. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe it was a griefe to the Ladies to haue that noted by publike taxation, which was as publikely noted &amp; obſerued by al men. If al ladies &amp; gentlewomen ſhold be ſo ſerued at any publike meeting, many wold make (if it were poſſible) their natural red of bluſhing ſhow through their painted red &amp; ouerlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mask of impudency &amp; boldnes. But wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, poore ſoules that haue nothing to bee proud of but their outward beautie, may be pardoned, if they ſeek to maintain their beſt hold, with anye deuiſe and addition of Arte, when as men who ſhould glorie onelye
<pb facs="tcp:12920:4"/>in their inward eſſence of worth and vertue, learning, prouidence, diſcretion, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, valoure, and magnanimitie, ſeeke to laye ſuch painted faces vpon their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſires they haue to be thoght worthy, in any to be admired or reſpected qualitie. Painting was in requeſt in <hi>Iezebels</hi> time, and her example could not, nor euer wil ſcare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way either pride from the heart, or painting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face. If I were of the noble ſcience of painters, I would put vp a bill againſt woe-men, for their intruſion into the profeſſion of facemaking and coulouring: but if I were a ſtates-man, I would publiſhe ſome ſeuere lawe, againſt ſuch bolde intruding profeſſors and ſhew-makers of ſuch thinges, as many gaine by boldnes and impudency, among the world both reſpect and commoditie. Heereafter I may happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take occaſion to ſpeake and ſet out your women painters, at this time you ſhall finde ſome painted faces of policy, deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered.</p>
            <p>As in meates, that which commonly
<pb facs="tcp:12920:4"/>liketh one doth diſtaſt another: ſo may this worke prooue like meats or banket-made-diſſhes, reiected of ſome, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like <hi>Homers</hi> Iliads be laid vnder other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pillowes. You rabble and ramping idle rout auaunt, the play-houſe-dores are now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen for you, the Author dooth not inuite your company to his feaſt, for he knowes you are apter to faſhion ſtrange interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of what was neuer meant, then like ciuil gueſts cut fairely and reſpectiuely of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. Howſoeuer he expoſeth this his <hi>Philaitetes</hi> to his good fortune, &amp; if any of the iudicious rank taſte of him with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he is filled vp &amp; regorged with ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend that was betrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the preſse of your cenſures <hi>I.M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:5"/>
            <head>In due praiſe of the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THeſe ſpeaking pictures of thoſe Counterfets,</l>
               <l>That would be ſtateſemen, rather men of <hi>State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are ſuch as doe their life delineate,</l>
               <l>By which the Drawers fame, ſtill life begets.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But where he paints in <hi>Colours</hi> (rarely rich)</l>
               <l>Tho Picture of a perfect ſtateſ-man, hee</l>
               <l>Tranſcends himſelfe, and makes each eye to ſee</l>
               <l>His darkeſt <hi>Vaines</hi> with iudgements cleareſt Touch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O nere could words, though weyed in wiſedoms ſcoles,</l>
               <l>And meaſurd by the ſquire of art, by Wit)</l>
               <l>But theſe alone, ſo right the ſpirit fit</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Stateſ-men</hi> that (obeying) all controlles,</l>
               <l>Paſſe on, <hi>viue image,</hi> make all Times admire,</l>
               <l>How earthly hands came by ſuch heauenly fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io: Dauis. Gent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:5"/>
            <head>In laudem Authoris.</head>
            <l>THy tun (deare friend) of wit &amp; hony nows brok vp,</l>
            <l>Too long fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men of Art &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, though lockt vp,</l>
            <l>For men of Art doe ſay, it taſtes right ſweete,</l>
            <l>And men of iudgements, ſay it is right ſound,</l>
            <l>And both a treaſure, ſay of light is found,</l>
            <l>A treaſure ſure that in extreames will ſteed.</l>
            <l>And raiſe thee (haue but patience) from all need,</l>
            <l>O pittie it is ſuch guifts and lights of minde</l>
            <l>Should be obſcurde, and die as men doe blinde.</l>
            <l>Some Scipio (or ſome Caeſar) ſhade thy hiue,</l>
            <l>That thou in ſpight of Waſpes and Flyes maiſt thriue.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>I.S. Gent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:6"/>
            <head>De Authore. <hi>T. P.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <hi>BLame not his pen, though wanton in his blood,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Here uels like a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin newly marryed:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pollicie is his delight, his ſtreaming flood</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>To that he is married, in that he ſhal be buried,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And though he buried were, this nere ſhall dye,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And though he baniſht were, this nere ſhall flye.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:6"/>
            <head>The contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>IIgnorant Politicians.</item>
               <item>Paules newes carriers, and vnlettered, but wickedly thriftie, merchants of worldlye policie with their iudgements.</item>
               <item>Vſurping Poets of the title of Pollicie.</item>
               <item>Vaine and ambitious Trauailers.</item>
               <item>Seminaries and Ieſuites.</item>
               <item>Cumberſome, Turbulent, and dangerous proiectors.</item>
               <item>True Stateſmen,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the ſecond part is treated</head>
               <item>Concerning the ſecret truſts of the heart.</item>
               <item>Concerning affections.</item>
               <item>Concerning booke truſt in Pollicie.</item>
               <item>Concerning cunning operations, and formall ordering of witte and Policie.</item>
               <item>Concerning a Politicians Religion, how farre he may wade therein.</item>
               <item>Concerning Religion, the beſt helpe of true Iudgement, and the true Religious pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litician.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preamble">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:7"/>
            <head>A SIXE-FOLDE Politician.</head>
            <p>There bee two ſortes of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians.</p>
            <p>Politicians in ſhew: and ſubſtantiall compleate experienced politicians. Otherwiſe called Stateſmen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Politicians</hi> in ſhew, and outward Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious profeſſion, are of many ſortes, as you ſhal finde them diſtinguiſhed by their ſeuerall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and Chapters.</p>
            <p>Subſtantiall <hi>Politicians,</hi> are ſuch (for this Treatiſe extends onely to a religious Common wealth) as are Diuinely indued with a ſinguler gift and blesſing of wiſedome &amp; iudgement, in all occurrences that may aduaunce the glory of God &amp; the common ſafetie of that State, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which they are ſet as Gouernours.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:8"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12920:8"/>
            <head>A SIX-FOLDE POLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICIAN.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>THE <hi>FJRST SORT</hi> of vaine Politicians are men voide of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet repute themſelues wiſe and politicke. CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He accurſed broode of CHAMS genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in the Land of <hi>Shinar,</hi> to make
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12920:9"/>bricke and morter; but ioyning with NIMROD, ſaide, Let vs make vs a SEM, which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a name, euen in deſpight of the bleſſing of NOAH beſtowed vpon SEM.</p>
               <p>All Nations, ages &amp; States, haue bene, and are, much peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the poiſonous humour of CHAMS fugitiue &amp; vnſetled ſeed, who ſhaking off all yoake of obedience, and preſcription of painfull trauel in any peculier calling, neuer think well of the ordinary bleſſings they reap or may reape, by their due &amp; daily labours: but ſetting their wittes beyond the pitch and model of their honeſt vocations,<note place="margin">Idlenes the mother of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable &amp; impertinent buſines.</note> ayme at extraordinary matters, the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to themſelues ſome SEM, or rather inſtead of a name, ſome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12920:9"/>BABEL or houſe of confuſion.</p>
               <p>And of names, none can ſo much pleaſe them as the title and ſtile of wittie, craftie, politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que trades, immitating heerein the grand deluder: for as Sathan of all names affecteth moſte the name of an Angel of light,<note place="margin">They which haue leaſt wit affect moſt the ſhew of the beſt wit.</note> &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſt of althings, appeareth moſte in the ſhowe of the beſt: ſo the ſimpleſt and furtheſt from the light of true wiſdome, deſire moſt to ſeeme (as Hypocrites in religion, being holloweſt of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſinceritie, affect moſte the ſhow of holineſſe) and to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wiſe.</p>
               <p>This maketh ſo many baſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicall fellowes, to fall from their laſts and meaſures, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out in their conceits &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uial co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferences, the ſcopes, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12920:10"/>&amp; intents of the ſecreteſt &amp; deepeſt miſteries of the moſte profound ſtatiſtes, and not onely to ſet a gloſſe and formall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation vpon ordinarie oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of the ſtate, and to preſſe out with them vaine and idle additions &amp; quotations, of their owne addle &amp; worme-ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten braines, but touching the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Edicts, Proclamations, yea, concluſions betwixt the State &amp; forraine Nations,<note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that falls vpon pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medlers with State affaires.</note> to diſtinguiſh &amp; point out errors, to ſet vppon them ominous predictions, and many times (which is the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch pragmatique and Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias like ſpirits fall into, as SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NECA noted the improuidence and vnaduiſedneſſe of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) <hi>Emittunt vices per iugulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dituras,</hi> caſt foorth cut-throate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12920:10"/>wordes which coſt them their necks, and vtterly vndoe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idle Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of newes.</note>The better to maintaine this opinion of ſelfe conceited Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and wiſdome, among the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſort, they muſt &amp; will be the onely intelligencers of all new accidents, <hi>Quelles nouelles</hi> is the onely oriſons they vſe morning and euening: their onely ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their onely graces. They know all things, elſe how ſhould they bee accounted ſtateſmen, both what is done and ſpoken in the court, &amp; in the center of the court, and which is wonderfull, that which was neuer done not ſpoken, and that makes their newes euer new and freſh, for it comes but from the gate of their owne inuentions.</p>
               <p>They are priuy to the conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12920:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Senate: embaſſages of Princes are familiar with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: intercourſe of marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts affaires, ſcarce accounted matters worth the diſcourſe: France, Italie, Spaine, can keep no Parliament, without their intermixture of voyces, nor this ſtate holde anye ſect of Parliament, without their verdict: theſe are the inſeperable companions of the <hi>realto</hi> pillars, the flies of the greate feaſts, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures third courſe to helpe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuperſtitious idolaters of Saint PAVL (and yet neuer think of PAVL nor any Apoſtle) and many of them haue that famous monument in that account as DIOGINES had IOVIS PORTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVS in <hi>Athens,</hi> who tould them, which wondered that he had no houſe nor corner to eat his meat
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12920:11"/>in; pointing at the gallerie or walking place that was called IOVIS PORTICVS, ſaid, that the people of <hi>Athens</hi> had builded that to his vſe, as a royall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for him, wherein he might dine &amp; ſup and take his repaſt.</p>
               <p>And ſo theſe make Paules like EVCLIDES or PLATOES ſchoole (as DIOGINES accounted it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a miſpending of much good la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour &amp; time, &amp; worthyly many times meet with DIOGINES fare, and are faithfull and frequent gueſts of Duke HVMPHRAY.</p>
               <p>And ſurely as that wiſe prince who adiudged his corrupt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant who ſould lip-labour and ſmoake at a deare rate, to be ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled with ſmoake; ſo might it be wiſhed that theſe idle buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marchants of ayre and ventoſity
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12920:12"/>of words, might be either prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like bladders, with the ſharpe raſor of ſome ſeueere lawe,<note place="margin">What puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is fit for ſellers of ſmoak &amp; lipla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured lies &amp; tales.</note> or Camelion like be forced to liue without any other ſuſtenance then ayre, the foode of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               <p>There are another ſorte of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letterd ignorants, who affect the title of politicians, and are ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of giddy muddye, and ſhallowe conceits, who ſee no more then that is obuious to their outward eye ſight: &amp; iudge all things by their effects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not the meanes by which they were effected:<note place="margin">It is an eaſie matter for a man moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettered, by wicked means to compaſſe great matters.</note> theſe are ſuch as by wicked &amp; indirect meanes, compaſſe many times great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whereunto is required ſmall ſtore of learning and arte: for it is an eaſie matter, for him to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12920:12"/>burne and make leuell to the ground, a famous city with a bal of wilde fire, who neuer had skil to diſtinguiſh the matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that ball was compoſed, or wit to contriue the like: and as a careleſſe creature, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds onely to praiſe his own humour, reſpecteth not the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe may inſue, may with great <hi>facilitie,</hi> ſet fire to an exquiſite peece of ordinance, and thereby beat downe ſome famous obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed building, who is vtterlye ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of any skilfull part of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerye: ſo may one that fell from a cloude, a moſt ſtupid animall, by wicked means bring to paſſe with aſmuch eaſe, his wicked purpoſes, and make himſelfe powerfull of his vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſhes, bee they neuer ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12920:13"/>who if hee were ſet to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage any affaires, that might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon good, would bray like an aſſe, and (admitted to deuiſing, aduiſing, or contriuing and putting in action, any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable &amp; deepe deſignement) ſtand like an immooueable ſtatua, ſcarce reſeruing the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and repreſentation of a man: For it is vſually ſpoken of courtiers, and Oratours, bee bould enough, and Courtier e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, prate enough, &amp; be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer (I meane cogging lawyer &amp; cogging courtier enough) ſo may it generally be ſaide, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to be wicked enough, and feare not to be acounted crafty and worldly, politicke enough, to prooue an <hi>Eutrapelus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud. Horat.</note> a famous crafty companion, and to exceed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12920:13"/>others in a watch of worldlye deceit, requireth onely a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be wicked, which wil ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily inable any man to proceed Maiſter in the art of ſubtilty, and cunning deceit: hence comes it to paſſe that many pettifogging knaues, many rurall Satyres, and vntutered Hobgoblings, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hearts to worldlye wealth, and reſoluing to obtain by right or wrong what they ſo longingly couet &amp; affect, proue ſuddainely rich, &amp; in that reſpect the ſimple people terme any, that by forgerye, couſning, deceite, growe a little wealthier, then their honneſt neighbours, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous heads, ſhrode fellowes, and (which without ſmiling I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider) polliticia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in this reſpect:<note place="margin">Miſchiefe hath ſwift wings.</note> miſchiefe is well ſaide to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12920:14"/>haue ſwift winges; for when the will of man giueth conſent to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euill, a very brute may quickly giue fire to the powder, &amp; matter of any miſchieuous purpoſe. <hi>Qui ſemel verecundiae fines tranſierit, in ſigniter eſſe impudente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oportet:</hi> So far the heathen could go, &amp; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we may ad this, that he which hath caſt away all care of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note place="margin">Honeſtie and fidelitie the chiefe pillers of al contracts</note> can haue no feeling or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of honeſtie and fidelitie, which in all affaires, either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or priuate, forraine or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtique, hold vp <hi>Atlas</hi>-like the heauen of all ciuil States, &amp; theſe being not reſpected, with what facilitie and eaſe may the ſubtill Courtier deceaue his brother, murder his father, if they ſtand in his way of ſome priuate reſpect, &amp; make his deareſt and boſome-friend,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12920:14"/>onelye an inſtrument to mooue forward his wicked pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes without anye purpoſe to helpe him in his greateſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: nay, if he think he may proue any obſtacle to his riſing, or that he can ſtand no longer as a foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole for him to mount vp to higher honour and dignitie, or a cloſe-ſtoole to ſmother and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey with coulerable excuſes his fouleſt and impureſt <hi>Feces</hi> of cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; deceite, euen then perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deouſlie to forſake him, when he is preſt with moſte vnreſiſtable difficulties.</p>
               <p>Among the number of theſe (that I may not ſpeake of neerer preſidents) is ranckt, that rancke ſmelling Pole-cat of impure and prophane pollicies, RICHARD the third, for it is well knowne,<note place="margin">Rich 3</note> that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12920:15"/>not ſo much a ſuperemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wit &amp; iudgement in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueſt ſtraines of ciuill gouerment, ſet the crowne on that vſurpers head, as a deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reſolution to compaſſe the ſame by any meanes, by poyſon, murder, periurie, barbarous and vnnatural cruelty, execrable ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, put a regal Scepter into his hande, and inuironed his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with a glittering Diadeam.</p>
               <p>And a ſecond to him may bee (if not a brother twinne,<note place="margin">Alphonſus</note> AL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHONSVS that foule bumcard-playing Politician, and 100. like to theſe: thoſe pettie Germane ſtate, affoord plenty of examples to this purpoſe: what ſhould I ſay when as the very Carter, vnder whoſe clouted ſhooes,<note place="margin">Wicked Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may bee accounted politicianst</note> may bee ſowed as greate craft when as firme a reſolution to villany and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12920:15"/>miſchiefe, is ſetled in him, can intitle himſelfe to his Vncles, brothers, nephewes, land and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and obtain it to, by leading a morice dance or two to hell, with fiue or ſixe forſworne good fellowes, himſelf foreman, a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt lawyer or two, as many bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed witneſſes, an ouerſeer and a ſeruant: which often tickles my diafragma, when I heare ſpruce-heere-at handes recount, conferring moſt ſecretly among their priuateſt &amp; moſt hidden obſeruations and court collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) the wonderfull wiſedome or pollicy of ſome great courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in auncient time, what admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matters they haue effected by the deepe reach of their all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peircing wits, when they were noted to haue vſed more ounces
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12920:16"/>of poiſon, then they had drams of true wiſedome, and ſtate lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in the ſhutting vp their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions: for thy conſider not that which daily experience may guide their obſeruation to, with what facility heatheniſh and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red conſciences,<note place="margin">The differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt the proceedings of a ſeered co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience and a Religious man</note> neuer ſo vnlette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red enter into and diſpatch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch ſauadge and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red qualities, as would make a man touched with the feeling of honeſty and a good conſcience, ſtand (were he neuer ſo politicke &amp; learned) at euery ſtep and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of the like attempts, like a multitude of people when vpon ſome ſudden inuaſion of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, all the Beacons of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are ſet on fire round about their eares, al amazed, affrighted, bepuſled, &amp; diſtempered euery
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12920:16"/>moment in his mutinous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered thoughts, till his plots, his purpoſes, his proceedings were diſcouered and betrayed, though to his own ruine and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vndoing.</p>
               <p>But heerein conſiſteth the iudgement ſuch ignorant and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettered affectators of the title of Polititians fall into:<note place="margin">preſumption the ground of ruine.</note> they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times preſuming vpon their owne and other mens falſe and flattering opinions conceaued of their great wiſdom &amp; policie, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by degrees into matters of greater conſequence then their ſlender apprehenſion s can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, and wraſtle through, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Maſtiffe, which becauſe by chance hee killed a Hare wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to his iawes by quick ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting hounds, would after chaſe a fox,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12920:17"/>and ſo came home all be torne &amp; rent with briars and brambles: or the ape which by imitation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing once ſet fire to a peece cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, came to inure himſelf in the like practiſe, and the peece being ſtopped &amp; ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bd hard of purpoſe that it might not go off, recoyled to the apes diſmenbring: ſo theſe hauing encountred with poorer and weaker vnderſtandings to their worldly and euill good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, not contented to keepe within the compaſſe of their owne element, ſtretch their skill &amp; cunning to intermeddle with men of deeper reaches &amp; more ſearching braines, whoſe fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like windings and turnings, they haue no skil to trace or ſent out, and therefore returne from their controuerſies and ſtrifes, made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12920:17"/>with ſuch worldly Mrs. of policy, all be ſcratched and pinched in their fortunes and effates. Yea, many of theſe fooliſh Ideots, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing proſpered and thriued in ſome domeſtick affaires, Ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like intermeddle with the fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes of court buſineſſe, and ſtate occurrences, imploy their wit and wealth in taking parte &amp; adhering to factions, &amp; ſo many times, being ignorant to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle &amp; finger as it were the cunning paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages &amp; ſtoppings of ſtate-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (which depends vpon ſuch exquiſit skil and harmony, as the ripe ſtudents therin can diſcern (as the Iewes could by their skil in the Ebrewtung any eſcape co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hiſtory of the bible) if any one ſtrok be out of time or tune) through bould intruſions,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12920:18"/>disbowell and diſmember them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their fortunes: and ſo much may ſuffice to haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ignorant and vnskilfull Vſurpers of the title &amp; name of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12920:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2. A ſecond ſort are ſuch as</hi> through the priuiledge of their learning and Schollerſhip, attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto them-ſelues the ſtile of <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abderitae</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Thrace,</hi> who were ſo fooliſh as they left their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie through annoyance of Mice.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſtippus</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of ſome ABDERITAN in what reſpect his ſonne ſhould bee the better, if he beſtowed coſt &amp; charges on his learning? anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, though in no other behoofe, yet that at the maygames &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſights there might not one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12920:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtone ſit vppon another: and to this alluded <hi>Tully</hi> in his <hi>Oratore,</hi> making the ſame deſtinction in the degree of excellency, betwixt a learned man and an ignorant,<note place="margin">A diſtinction betwixt a lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned man and anignorant.</note> as betwixt an ordinary man and a beaſt: and queſtionles the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of learning and skill in artes and liberall ſciences, is of greate and vnualuable eſtimate, and bringeth to the enioyers thereof,<note place="margin">The benefit of learning.</note> many vnſpeakable &amp; inſencible helpes and furtherances, which as it was wel ſpoken of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of health, <hi>Care<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do potius quamfru e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do diſtingu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur,</hi> their vſe is beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by their wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But learning is like to fire &amp; water,<note place="margin">Learning like fire and water for the vſe and abuſe of it.</note> which are moſte neceſſary for the daily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life, being moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; deſcretly vſed, otherwiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimpleſt, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12920:19"/>if they be applyed to hurtful pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, there are not more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and dreadfull Elements.</p>
               <p>That made <hi>Diogines</hi> very iuſtly (in my opinion) to affirme,<note place="margin">Man the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and the fooliſheſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature.</note> that there was no liuing thing wiſer then man, nor any liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fooliſher: for when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and thought vppon the gouernours of Cities, phiſitians, and men excelling in ſeueral profeſſions of learning, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded nothing to be more ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent then man; but when he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in his minde men of little learning in any profeſſion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of all learning, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to performe any one good, vndertakers of all difficult and hard enterpriſes, when he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the ſwarme of expounders of dreames, ſoothſayers, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12920:20"/>and deluding artizants, he plainely auouched that nothing was more fooliſh then man. And ſurly as there are none wiſer then Schollers, &amp; none fooliſher then ſuch like ſchollers, ſo are there none more profitable to the Common-wealth nor anye more comberſome, noiſome or troubleſom in a ſtate, then ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: which infers well this Ianus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like poſition, <hi>Peſsimi homines peſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma animalia. peſsimi Academici peſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi homines.</hi> Of all liuing creatures euill men are the worſt, and of all men euill Schoole-men are the moſte diſorderly and hurtfull.<note place="margin">The wit of man liable to good and euill</note>
               </p>
               <p>For the wit of man is appliable, and apt to all goodnes, if it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed and inured therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but if it fall from his right kinde to vice, then is a man
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12920:20"/>worſe then a brute beaſte in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that a beaſt doth but beaſtly acording to kinde,<note place="margin">A vicious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe then a beaſt.</note> &amp; a mans wit aplyed to a vitious &amp; beaſtly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome traines vp all the ſences, as it were ſo many workmen, to the practiſing of naughtie and lewd purpoſes: and if the wit of a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie man, well ſeene in arts, and helped and furthered to greater vnderſtanding by ſtudye, be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to wicked and euill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes,<note place="margin">A wicked wittie man moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> it will alwaies be ſitting vpon Cockatrices eggs, &amp; hatch and bring forth nothing but ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine and poiſonous effectes. with both theſe ſorts of ſchollers this ſtate is much peſtered, for it harbours many fooliſh, ſuch as ſeeme &amp; are indeed wiſe in their owne conceits (ſuch as trouble a whole ſtate with their conceites) &amp; many naughty and lewd wits,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12920:21"/>that aply their coſt &amp; trauel ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t painefully and laboriouſly in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall arts, to the contriuance of their countries maſſaker and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and their owne ſhame and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter demolition.</p>
               <p>That I may not of theſe ſpeak confuſedly &amp; without order, I will reduce the firſt ſort of them to theſe heades.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Either vaine phanaicall ſcribling Poets,</l>
                  <l>Or cunny-catching &amp; prating Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailers.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And the ſecond ſort to theſe heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Either out-landiſh starters &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers from their obedience and loyaltie vſually called</hi> Ieſuites <hi>and</hi> Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>or cloſe houſe-keeping, either vaine-glorious or ſelfe pleaſing, or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12920:21"/>malignant, enuious, turbulent proiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and plotters of policies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> It was well noated of <hi>Heſiodus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idlenes abhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red.</note> that no courſe of honeſt trauell was ſhame-worthy, but idlenes, full of reproach and ſhame: and certes, if men of faſhion and good bringing vp, would duely examine themſelues to what honeſt and profitable ſeruice and courſe of labour, they were fit, and accordingly would ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly endeuour themſelues, they wold make this ſtate hapy &amp; flou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſhing, &amp; their owne liues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to themſelues and their friends: but the iniquity of theſe times is ſuch, and ſo corrupted is this age with cymerian darkenes and ſelfe will, as many hauing any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12920:22"/>good parts, thinke ſcorne in <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis tertijſque conſiſtere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambition and aſpiring, raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſte povver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</note> Euery Crowe will build as high as the Eagle, and thereby with <hi>Icarus,</hi> ſoaring to high, melt their waxie winges, with the Sunbeames of too lofty aſpiring practiſes, which makes ſo many of them al theire liues after,<note place="margin">The fruites of aſpiring.</note> ſing <hi>Icarus</hi> his ditties, <hi>Propter humum volito</hi> lye groueling in a bare &amp; baſe eſtate: for whilſt they ſtriue to run out of their father <hi>Adams</hi> curſe, and by him the curſe which deriueth it ſelfe to all mankinde (which was and is euery man in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to get his liuing by the ſweat of his browes) they run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a greater curſe, that is, either through idlenes to get no liuing, or through ſome euil practiſe to beget a baſe liuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:12920:22"/>
               <head>Of Poets. CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Poets liues compared to loue.</note>TOuching POETS, their liues and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes may be rightly compared, to the buſines of loue: for loue is noated to be the occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and buſines of idle folkes, that haue nothing els to ſet them ſelues on worke withall: for as the paſſion of loue eſpecially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uades and poſſeſſeth ſuch men as are altogether drowned in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſo commeth it to paſſe,<note place="margin">Otis ſi tollas periere cupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis arcus.</note> that while they giue themſelues wholy to lazines, they ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble on a ſubiect, that filleth their heads
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12920:23"/>as full of combrous buſines, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they are able to turne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto: ſo this frenſie of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etaſtring (for poetry and iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous poets, al worthy ſpirits alow and loue) ſtill inuadeth the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of idlenes, for, whileſt that wit which is pregnant,<note place="margin">A pregnant wit wanting imployment takes hould of naughty cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> wanteth all manner of imployment, it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into a moſt troubleſome, &amp; inextricable maze of ſelfe-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and deluding conceits: for it may &amp; is generally obſerued, that they which once fal into the humour of vercifiing, their heads are alwaies ful of as manye cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets, as new ſtrooken louers, &amp; ſurly for the reſpect &amp; regard the moſt iudicious haue: of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The regard the iudicious haue of vaine poets.</note> they may be compared to inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts alwaies out of tune, which yeeld but harſh and iangling accents,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12920:23"/>and to men duely conuerſant in weightie and profitable affaires, they are as flat and tedious, as <hi>Iarchthange,</hi> which name is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the harſheſt in all the Ebrew pronuntiation, and the reſpect which the wantoneſt and vaineſt heads haue of them, is as of fidlers, who are regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but for a bandy ſong, at a merry meeting, and when they haue done, are commonly ſent away with Butlers grace, when theſe write beſt, they are but but buſily conuerſant, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about ſome ill ſubiect, which is but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a iugling fooliſh play,<note place="margin">Ill, the better acted, the vvorſe liked of the good.</note> the better it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the worſe it is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for: either they write to pleaſe idle vaine gentlemen and gentlewomen, and ſo may bee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12920:24"/>placed among the number of ſhitle-cocks, tennis-balles, apes, munkies, baboones parrats, pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets,<note place="margin">Vaine poets offices.</note> and ſuch like (their office hauing correſpondence to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other vſe &amp; purpoſe) or els they faſhion their wits to the pleaſing of a vaine multitude, and rabbell of looſe liuers, and preſcribe to the ignorant and ſimple (very ill diſpoſed of themſelues) rules, and rudiments of worſe liuing: and as the enterludes may be tearmed,<note place="margin">Vaine poets and plaiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in euill</note> the Schoole-houſes of vanitie, and wantonnes; ſo theſe are the ſchoolemaiſters thereof: and me thinks they (who haue taſted of the ſweete fountaine water, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from their Academick mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers breaſts, by this, if nothing elſe) ſhold be deterred from their ſcribling profeſſion, that they ſee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12920:24"/>their writings &amp; conceits ſold at a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon doore to euery baſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for a penny. But moſt of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits are too deere at that rate, and therefore may well bee had in the ſame requeſt that To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco is now, which was wont to be taken of great gentlemen, &amp; gallants, now made a frequent &amp; familiar Companion of euerye Tapſter and Horſe-keeper. And their conceits are likeſt Tobacco of any thing: for as that is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kindled, makes a ſtinking ſmoake, &amp; quickly goes out, but leaues an inhering ſtinke in the noſtrils and ſtomackes of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,<note place="margin">Conceits ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of no iudgment or ſtuddie like Tobacco ſmoke.</note> not to be drawne out, but by putting in a worſe fauour, as of Onions and Garlick, (according to the prouerbe: the ſmel of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke takes away the ſtink of dung
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12920:25"/>hils, ſo the writing of ordinarye Play-bookes, Pamphlets, &amp; ſuch like, may be tearmed the muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceptions of idle braines, moſte of them are begotte ouer night in Tobacco ſmoake and muld-ſacke, and vttered and deliuered to the worlds preſſe by the helpe &amp; midwifery of a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the next morning.</p>
               <p>They ſauour of no ſtudy, and leſſe iudgement, and leaue to the hearers of them onely, an infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtincke of ſome lewd practiſe or ſpeech, ſet forth for the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of ſuch wits, as delight in no other ſtudye but folly or wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes,<note place="margin">How the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people delight in vile and vaine ſports.</note> and will not bee drawne out of their mouthes and mawes (for yron would bee ſooner by ſome diſgeſted then a fooliſh rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baldrie tearme by ſome loſt) till
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12920:25"/>from the like impure fountaine, they haue fetched ſome freſh mud-water of the like,<note place="margin">Vaine poets colour their euill purpoſes vnder the ſhew of grauitie and authoritie, vvherein they approoue themſelues moſt Diueliſh and though moſt politicke in their ovvne opinions, yet moſt fooliſh in the true ſenſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</note> or worſe (but better pleaſing, if more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure) ſpeach or behauiour, to occupy and fill vp that roome.</p>
               <p>But ſome of theſe phanaticall heades, to exempt themſelues from the number of ballad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and ordinary writers of Iigs and ſuch like ſtuffe, betake themſelues to a grauer and more ſatiricall forme of writing and therefore vnder the pretence of whipping the vices of people, with a pen fuller of gall,<note place="margin">as Horace ſaith.</note> 
                  <hi>Sublimi flagello,</hi> they will either ſet out in moſt liuely colours,<note place="margin">vvith a vvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter rod.</note> all the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall impieties and impurities, which they haue in their liues ran thorough (for it is impoſſible any ſhould ſo exactly to a hayre
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12920:26"/>ſet out ſuch boſome ſecretes of lewd practiſes, but ſuch as haue had a deepe finger in the like) or elſe out of a deſire to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted great politicians, fet their wits beyond the pitch of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary tenters, and intermingle not onely (as <hi>Horrace</hi> ſaith) <hi>Sacra prophanis</hi> ſiluer ſacers, with durty potlids, but (thinking that <hi>Picto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus at que poetis quidlibet audendi</hi> is ſtill in force, that painters may play with their penſils with great mens noſes, and poets may piſh in any mans face) intermeddle with the 2. edged ſworde of the ſtate,<note place="margin">Many had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ieſt away their credits &amp; liues then looſe the opinion of a ieſt.</note> and contrary to <hi>Quintilians</hi> precept (who placed it among the vertues and graces of wrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, not to ſay all a man can) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ignorant of the ſtate, &amp; mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12920:26"/>concerning the ſtate, they will in their broad tearmes pull the greateſt ſtatiſts by the beards and rather then they will looſe a ieſt in obſcurity, fixe it about the Princes Diadem, that it may be knowne and ſeene of all men, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting what they learnd of olde Poet <hi>Homer,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> It is not ſafe drawing out of Lyons teeth.<note place="margin">Both learning and obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on teach the wiſe to holde their pens and their tongues from princes &amp; potentates af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faires.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And if they had attained either learning or obſeruation in ſtate affaires, and true policie (the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute whereof many of them ſo much affect) they would houlde their pens from the affaires and actions of ſtatesmen, beeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the <hi>Hectors</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> of the common wealth (according to that atribute which was giuen by <hi>Homer</hi> to <hi>Hercules</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:12920:27"/>depulſors of euill, through their wiſdome and carefull watching ouer the quiet and welfare therof, from the whole nation. For then they wold haue learned by their reading of hiſtories,<note place="margin">Both Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hated to come vpon the tongues &amp; pens of triuiall and common men.</note> (which is the beſt Booke-help for a ſtudent in policy) that both AVGVSTVS and ALEXANDER tooke verie greeuouſlie that any thing ſhold be made of them, and ſet forth in publique, but after a ſubſtantiall ſort. And how AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS to the officers of his time ſignifyed his pleaſure, that they ſhould not ſuffer any point of op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>probrie to come vnto his name, by the meeting and comming together of Ieſters, Players, and Poets: and as well by obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in politicke courſes, they would haue vnderſtood that it is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12920:27"/>as fit (and more neceſſarie for the ſafetie of any ſtate) for the authoritie of Princes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of the common-wealth,<note place="margin">The authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of princes and gouernors may not ſafely admit any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation.</note> euerie where to bee maintained in their royall ſtate, without any manner of ſpot or touch of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, either publique ſpred, or cloſly inſinuated (for in either conſiſts <hi>laeſa maieſtas,</hi> or <hi>poteſtas Reipub:</hi> a high and capitall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to the Prince or his poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates) as a virgins chaſtitie,<note place="margin">Libelling, and how far the offence therof ſpreds it ſelfe.</note> and a great Ladies honour, which may not admitte the leaſt ſuſurres or priuie whiſperings of ſtain or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation, and as he that ſhold be the firſt author of ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalizing any great Ladies vnſpotted worth &amp; reputation of chaſtity, would be adiudged by the parliament of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſome infamous deth, ſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12920:28"/>were it fit that ſome ſeueere law might be enacted,<note place="margin">Scandalous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling &amp; tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſtates<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, deſerueth the ſame pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as the abuſers of a chaſt Ladies honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</note> for the puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of ſuch ſcandalous libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as is, or may be at any time coloured vnder the name of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etiſing, and play-making, <hi>Sed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primo me,</hi> onely I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point without this ingenious and true apologie in my owne behalfe, to ſhew that my deſire is, it may not bee thought that I houlde the skill &amp; art of poetry in baſe acount,<note place="margin">poetry to be be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the abuſers therof to be puniſhed</note> but onely the abuſers of it. Poetry may be both noblemens &amp; ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers afternoone, and ſucceſſiue excerciſes, &amp; remiſſion from the bent of grauer ſtudies and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A ſpeciall rule for poets to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue.</note>And if any will and muſt needes make it their profeſſion, let them hould this comicall rule concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12920:28"/>the ſtate and ſtatiſts, <hi>Sic haec miſceant vt illa non immiſceant,</hi> Let them ſo vſe their quaint conceits as they may picke no qua rell with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:29"/>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12920:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. Concerning Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat of <hi>Horace, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum non animum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat qui trans mare currit,</hi> hee that chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his ſoyle, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not his ſoule, was wel noted of SOCRATES. For SOCRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES hearing a certaine perſon complaining, that his trauelling into ſtrange Countries for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; knowledge, had nothing auailed him, anſwered that it cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnto him very deſeruedly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12920:30"/>for that he either applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the company of idle run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agating fellowes or elſe mew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe vp, and kept priuate, as if he tooke phiſicke, thinking that the ayre of a ſtrange country would infuſe ſtrange languages, riper Witte,<note place="margin">What maketh a mans trauell into ſtrange countries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and what vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> and Iudgemente without conuerſing with ſuch as were wiſe and iudicious; or elſe wanted wit to obſerue ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, as the conuerſation of wiſe and graue iudgements did affoord. For one of thoſe three makes a mans trauell fruitleſſe, For whoſoeuer in any ordinarie profeſſion entendeth to reape a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny skill and knowledge, by enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with other nations, muſt examine his owne ſtrength of witte, whether it be capable of the skill and art, he intendeth and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12920:30"/>deſireth to attaine, &amp; muſt ſettle his affections, and bridle the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of pleaſure and raging extrauagant humors that rule in his nature,<note place="margin">What general lie is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of a trauailer.</note> that thereby hee may be able both to reſolue himſelfe to a ſtudious and paineful courſe of exerciſe and obſeruation, and alſo to be wary and circumſpect of the choice of his companye, leaſt he light vpon natures, not ſo skilfull and well ſeene in the Arte and miſterie he couets to learne, as ſubtill and full of pleaſing ſhewes and deluſions, which are by them made both cunning purſnets &amp; hartnets, to inueagle and intrap young nouices by.</p>
               <p>This haue manye Iewellers, Phiſitians, young vntamed Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Schollers pregnant, but vnskilfull of the courſe of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12920:31"/>worlde, had woefull experience of.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for him that intendeth by trauelling to attaine knovvledge in ſtate learning.</note>But they which intend to make progreſſe by trauelling in the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſtate learning, muſt not onely haue a capacitie fit for the entertaining all ſtratagemicall plots and deuiſes, that may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to their conſideration, and abilitie to quell, and ſuppreſſe all diſordered motions and affectes, but muſt be throughly inſighted both in the Theorie of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and moſt ſubſtantial points of all policy,<note place="margin">Cunning po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians are like true Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymiſts not ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or free to relate their miſticall and wel digeſted poſitions.</note> and alſo well experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in the particuler liues, qualities and policies of his owne countrie chiefeſt and deepeſt Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, that thereby in conuerſing with profounder iudgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad (who vſe not in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes to make Academical lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12920:31"/>and comments, but miſtically and as it were in a cloude to inuolue their quaint conceits and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they may be able in the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a hand, to vnfolde and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, that which may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to their quicke vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, worthy obſeruation, and giue vnto them they conuerſe withall, a taſte of the like iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">The learned and skilfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of their like.</note> and inſight anto politicke affaires, which breedes in great wits &amp; men of deeper vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mutual content and ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and workes through the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry marrowe and <hi>pericran yon</hi> of the wiſeſt and ſoundeſt heads, and laſtly muſt be furniſhed with ſuch iudgement, as may make him able in a moment, to diſcerne a redde from a ſtammell, and not to ſpend either time or coſte vppon any
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12920:32"/>vain-glorious, friuolous, delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mountibankes, and ſhowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers of policy, and ſtate-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as many haue a good will to learne, and want wit to conceaue, and abilitie to temper their affections, and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ouer-rule their vnbridled partes, and many hauing a good and ready wit, and abilitie to fit their humours to all occaſions, yet diuert, and incline both their wit &amp; will to ſiniſter &amp; bye cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the former ſorte prooue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wiſer but in ſhew, the other onely wiſer in wicked and crafty contriuances, and yet both muſt returne great ſtates-men and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians.<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine and for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mal trauailers compared to vvanton and fooliſh acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mickes.</note> The former like freſh gentlemen Academickes, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue learned by heart, but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12920:32"/>
                  <hi>Porpheries predicables,</hi> and <hi>predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> &amp; by a ſophiſticated argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can include (ſcarce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) their fathers ſcullio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at their return home in <hi>Bocardo,</hi> think the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues learned enough, but more like baſe timerous motly Croſſe wearers (for they are not worthy the title of Soldiers) ſuch as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> had at the ſiege or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or rock in the Indies, ſo impregnable as they admired, but feared to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vpon it) who hauing looked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A</hi> deſcription of prating ſouldiers and Braggarts.</note> whether they were preſt to wage war in, and gotten by heart the names of the chiefe Commanders, leaders, Captaines, Leiftennants, and ſuch like, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with as great a brag, as if by their vertue and proweſſe, Sa. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingo,</hi> or ſome other hould of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall note had bene taken: and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12920:33"/>vpon their faces ſome ſcuruy Deuill-like viſards of ſterneſſe, &amp; taking into their mouthes canon oathes, will among the ſimpler vppon their ale-benches, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the onely powder and ſhot-men, &amp; experteſt martialiſts of ten thouſand, being indeede as we commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly cal them hot-ſhots, and haue more skill in the letting off a duzzen riggleſworthes dags well fild with ſacke, then in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging one Calliuer, and know the way better, and had rather march by night to the Iland of Cranes, then ſayle by day to the Eaſt or Weſt Indies: ſo theſe firſt ſorte of fooliſh trauellers, if they can but recite the names of many faire townes they haue paſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,<note place="margin">Bragging tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bribed.</note> giue their friend at their returne a french ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12920:33"/>it be with a french bow in the hams) and cut their meat after an Italian faſhion, weare their hat &amp; feather after a Germaine hufty, tell with a good grace, or rather bould face, not a hundred &amp; fifty merry tales, (for then they would take away the gentleman fooles office) but fiue hundred lies, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe with thoſe lies and cogges good cloathes, and alter the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion often: they muſt and wilbe eſteemed the onely wiſe, learned, languaged politicians: and great reaſon, for why, among men of the ſimpler and ſmoother condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who think any man (though but as wiſe as a Parrat, that can change his la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage very learned) they ſticke not to giue out, that they are cloſe and priuate, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther priuy intelligencers (and yet
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12920:34"/>their continuall prating &amp; taking all occaſions to keepe their new found tongues,<note place="margin">Continuall prating, an argument of follie and ſmall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> in euerlaſting motion, ſhewes that they doe neither <hi>intelligere,</hi> nor can giue any intelligence of worthy note) and that they may diſpend of ſome worthy Senators purſe (who neuer heard of their names) ſo many Crownes <hi>per annum,</hi> and there-vpon fill for more likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſake, their pockets full of amorous loue lines, and taylors and tauernes vnpaid reckonings, and ſeale them vp as if they were letters of ſpeciall coherence and intelligence, lately poaſted, not ſent, from ſome great out-landiſh fauourites:<note place="margin">Braging tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed.</note> and many times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong weaker iudgements (not vnlike pettie broking marchants that trade in the enterchange of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12920:34"/>brooches, currals, hobbi-horſes, painted babies, and dogges, who when they come into the country giue out they are ſubſtantial mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and ſo paſſe for currant, in the beliefe of the ſimpler (beeing where they dwel and are knowne, accounted and called but plaine pedlers:) through ſuch ſleight de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, they gaine the opinion of wiſe and politicke linguiſts; but when they meet with any of worthe, iudgement, and repute, they are held (as they are) baſe mimicke anticke affectators and meere faſhion-mongers.</p>
               <p>But theſe affecting Politicians are leaſt offenſiue to the ſtate, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely ſelfe pleaſers of their owne vaine &amp; idle humours, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in this regard they bee hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that beeing like Cipreſſe trees,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12920:35"/>neither good for building, nor bearing fruite: with their faire leaues they ouerſhadow better mens roomes and places.<note place="margin">Idle men in a common vvealth like Cipreſſe trees.</note> 
                  <hi>Fruges conſumere nati,</hi> fruitles conſumers of wealth and words.</p>
               <p>The latter ſorte of trauellers are more troubleſome and noyſome to the common wealth, for they hauing both wit and abilitie to ad to their ſtudie in ſtate-learning good &amp; profitable obſeruations, by trauelling into other countries and returning not onely well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with many helpes of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and forraine languages,<note place="margin">Diſcontented vvittie and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers dangerous and noiſome to any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vvealth.</note> but with ſubſtantiall matter of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe diſgeſted out of ſuch gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occurrences as haue happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thoſe partes, where they ſpent their time, thinke now there is but one ſtep betwixt them
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12920:35"/>and the chaire of ſtate: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſcorne to conuerſe with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelopes</hi> handmaides, will courte none but <hi>Penelope</hi> herſelfe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they were admitted to any high place of gouernement, in the common wealth, and put to the teſt of true iudgement and knowledge in the ſtate, they wold prooue ſo far from Troy-weight as being ballanced with a true, wiſe and experienced ſtates-man, in any perticuler, great &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie buſines, they would not proue currant to paſſe in any the leaſte affaires of a thouſand, that ſhold be propounded. They imagine not what difference is betwixt <hi>Platoes</hi> cups and tables, and his cuppitees and tabletees, the one fit for euery ordinary ſcholler to diſcourſe of, the other able to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12920:36"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found the deepeſt iudgements and profoundeſt artiſtes.</p>
               <p>The ordinarie and generall propoſitions maximees, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe of ſtate affaires,<note place="margin">Onely vviſe experienced ſtateſmen to be admitted to the graue and vveightie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the common-vvealth.</note> is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of diſcourſe for the trauailer and Student in pollicye, but the cuppitees &amp; tablettees as it were of particuler I deas, and deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in &amp; belonging to a ſtate, is only matter for the ripeſt and moſte experienced ſtates-men, to diſcouer, intermeddle, &amp; diſpute of.</p>
               <p>Euerie man that can looke (as DEMOSTHENES ſaide to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THENIANS of PHILOXENVS his arriual) againſt a candle, may not thinke his eyes firme enough to gaze againſt the Sun: onely of the deepe diſcerning politician it muſt be ſaide, <hi>tam cernit acutim
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12920:36"/>quam aut aquila aut ſerpens Epidau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> ſuch as haue ſuch inſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the State as by indirections they can finde directions out, though they were hid fathome deepe.</p>
               <p>Euerie man can ſay that a good Chyrurgion muſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times launch deepe, ſometimes infuſe oyle into a wound, but none but a perfect &amp; skilful chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tel when to diſtinguiſh thoſe different times and ſeaſons. Euerie Apothecarie &amp; hearbiſt can diſcourſe that this hearb is good for that greefe, and that for another, but to draw poiſon from the roote, and to make a pleaſant ſallet from the vpper part of one and the ſelfe ſame hearb, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely to a moſt skilfull &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Phiſition: ſo theſe by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12920:37"/>reading, obſeruation and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, had with learned &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men abroad, can relate that it is preſcribed ſometimes to haue as graue a countenance as <hi>Phoci on</hi> or <hi>Democritus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not to know much, but to mode rate the knovvledge of much, is true knovvledge.</note> and that <hi>Lyourg us</hi> himſelfe allowed, ſometimes a merry and cheereful behauiour: but when to be ſad of geſture, &amp; when to ſmile, and giue place to mirth, and laughter, they can hardly preſcribe themſelues that moderation. For their mirth and pleaſant Iocondnes moſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taſteth of Scurilitie, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes and apiſh effeminatenes: &amp; their ſadneſſe ful of affectation and harboring, not ſo deepe, as dangerous matters touching the ſtate.</p>
               <p>They haue obſerued by reading good hiſtories and conference,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12920:37"/>that IVLIVS CAESAR ſaid, that matters of high enterpriſe,<note place="margin">He is truly wiſe that can diſtinguiſh rightly the times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of vſing his theorie in perti cular acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſubiect vnto great and vncertain dangers, ought to be executed and diſpatched out of hand, and no aduiſe and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration to be taken of them, in regard that to the going through with buſines of that nature, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie dooth greatly helpe: the caſting in of many demurres to matters of great peril, doth pluck a man back from hardy &amp; aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing: and they haue obſerued- &amp; can diſcourſe by the reading and conference on the contrary, that DOMITIVS CORBVLO v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed much to ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Domitius Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulo</hi> his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of vvar.</note> that a mans ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in battaile were to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with a carpenters ſquaring axe, that is to ſay ſoking lye, one peece after another, and by both
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12920:38"/>theſe obſeruations laide toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, can perhaps at their returne in their conferences drawe out theſe concluſions, that a Statſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man either in matters of war or imployments of peace, muſt ſometimes be ſudden, ſometimes full of deliberation, ſometimes ſlowe, ſometimes peremptorie, and reſolute: but if they were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to particuler deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch or the like ſtate dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, as often happen to the deuiding Iudgement of graue &amp; experienced States-men, either in matters of peace or war, they would be as farre to ſeeke when to cut with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon axe, which goes through at the firſt chop, &amp; when to vſe the ſquaring axe, which worketh the ſame effect by little and little, as how to vſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12920:38"/>the Carpenters Square, or Axe, without cutting their legges off.</p>
               <p>If therefore they would accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to SOCRATES his precept, (who thoght it moſt againſt reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any man to ſet vp any handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft or occupation before ſuch time as he had throughly learned the ſame, or for a Seafaring man to ſit and holde the Sterne of a ſhip, before hee had full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect experience in the feate of Marinerſhip) applye themſelues to the skilfull and expert Card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of a ſtate,<note place="margin">Men that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to proue skilfull in anye courſe muſt apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the moſt skilfull &amp; experienced in euery kinde.</note> and become as it weare their apprentiſes before they ſet their hands and heads to the contriuance and making of curious neſts of boxes &amp; exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite drawers &amp; cubberds, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſecret learning of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique gouernement; obſeruing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12920:39"/>PLVTARCHS rule, <hi>vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntes ſequi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius quam caecos ducere,</hi> followe the ſound rather then like a lame cripple leade the blinde, they might then happilye attaine in time, that which vaine-glorie detayneth) profunditie of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and expect skill in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the weightieſt affaires of the common wealth.</p>
               <p>Apothecaries haue many bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of moſte eccellent receipts hanging vp in their ſhops, ſuch as they know haue cured manye ſeuerall malladies: and they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand which receite cured one ſicke of a feauer, which the ſtopping of the liuer, which a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thare, but yet beeing not able to iudge whether the cathare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a colde and humid fluxe, or a hot &amp; drie diſtemper in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12920:39"/>the liuer or lungs, or what origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſe and predominant qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie the Feuer and other ſeuerall diſeaſes-did proceede, dare not preſume without the ſpeciall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Doctor, whoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued skill and long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath attained to the depth of all cauſes, to miniſter any maner of Phiſicke to patient and ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected bodies: and ſurely if theſe could obſerue the Apothecaries rule,<note place="margin">Diſcontent &amp; pride, ouer-throvve many good parts.</note> to be contented to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring handes to the Doctors in policie and State-learning, they might then perhaps proceede in time to the pulſe of the State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, a degree further then the diſcreete and wiſe Apothecaries euer aſpire vnto: or if not ſo, they may ſettle themſelues in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable courſe of ſome honeſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12920:40"/>and warrantable account, to their owne comfortes, and the good (in ſome meaſureand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) of the common wealth. But when like quick-ſaluers they ſtriue to be accounted doctors, becauſe they haue trauailed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ſea, and skimbd vp two or three excellent receipts, they drawe to themſelues either by vaine-glory, ſuch diſcredit as quicke-ſaluers haue in all theyr vndertakings, or run (through diſcontentment that they may not haue ſuch dignitie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion as they deſire, and they onely think they deſerue) into ſuch baſe offices and courſes, as diſcredits and diſables all the worth and repute which either their trauailing or ſtudy might bring vnto them, and ſo become
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12920:40"/>not as the other ſort of trauailers were, like timerous, but like lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſturdy ſouldiers, who hauing bene in many hot skirmiſhes, &amp; behaued themſelues by ſea or land like gallant tall men, yet are far from true skill and millitarie diſcipline, becauſe they may not haue that place and commaund which belongeth to a man, not onely of a ſtout courage, but an experte and skilfull commander, betake themſelues to piracie or robbing by the high way, the high way to their vndooing: ſo theſe (application I neede make little) the meaneſt vnderſtanding and conceit can apply it, and I would they whome it moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes, would apply it to their hearts, and prooue wiſer in their courſes, not profuſely and prodigally abuſing thoſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12920:41"/>good parts, which if they were purged with the fire of ſtayednes from vanitie, would ſhine and glitter about them, like the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt armour,<note place="margin">Learning well vſed brings both ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</note> both to their excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glory and exaltation, and alſo to the defence and propul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many indignities, which they through their owne folly ſuſtaine; ſo theſe I ſay by fayling of their vnderſerued longings, fall either to the ſecret profeſſion and practiſing with young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, ſuch Aretin, or ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatching mountebancke-like-tricks, as they haue learned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas, as drowne and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoint the fruites of all their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and dilligent obſervations, made about ſtate buſines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:12920:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. 5. Touching Seminaries and Ieſuits.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Vnc venio ad grauisſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam et atrocisſimam querelam no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meam ſed reipub. grauiſsimam</hi> in reſpect of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and weakeneſſe of ſome, atrociſſimam in reſpecte of the obſtinate peruerſenes and wilfull reſolution of others of this coat and profeſſion:<note place="margin">The vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralnes of our countrimen vvhich becom Ieſuits.</note> It was ſaide of <hi>Romulus,</hi> that hee grewe hardye, rough and ſterne, being caſt out to be bred of hardy, fierce &amp; ſauadge beaſts,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12920:42"/>and that was no maruaile: and it is ſet down likewiſe that <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> turned poyſonous hearbes and receipts into wholeſome nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, by inuring his bodie to take and eat poyſon, &amp; that was no maruaile:</p>
               <p>But for men bred of the ſweete milke of their mother country, to turne bloody and murderous cut-throats of her proſperitie, and flouriſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: for men trained vp among the wholeſome and pure nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſweete and profitable inſtructions, to be either by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſeduced, or through deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wilfulnes reſolued, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſe vnrecouerably their wits and ſtudies, in the contriuance of nothing but poyſon, and poyſonnous plottes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12920:42"/>and Serpent-like to rippe vppe the bowels of their owne natiue parent and milke-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſoyle: theſe are <hi>Execranda prodigia, &amp; prodigioſa monſtra,</hi> Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable prodegies, &amp; prodigious and fearfull abbortiue monſters of nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. ſortes of monſters or monſtrous Seminaries.</note>I haue implicitiuely noted two ſorts of theſe monſters: The former, of them are preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but weake vnderſtandings, pregnant and appliable to euil, as wax in ſommer, ready of it owne accorde to ſticke to any matter: but to good, honeſt and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courſes, either concerning themſelues, or their country,<note place="margin">pregnant but in conſtant &amp; vnſetled wits how affected.</note> as waxe in winter, brickle and hard and of much difficultie to bee wrought, with either alluring perſwaſions, or chafing inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12920:43"/>and like children to goe from ſchoole; vppon the report of many gay and pleaſing ſights to be ſeene beyond the ſeas they are wonne to leaue the land with an apple, but to ſit ſtil at home in ſome ſtade and honeſt profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, like children hard to be won with gould to goe to ſchoole, and ſit all day in ſecurity and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, learning that which may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance their good for euer: and when they are drawne out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ſeas, and haue pleaſed their eyes with the ſight of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding maſſe-ſhewes, and ſuch like trumpery, as are euery where obuious, and haue got a ſmacke of that obſceene, impure, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie life, they prooue like mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grell dogges,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A</hi> deſcription of a lazie life.</note> rather perſwaded (according to that ſaying of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12920:43"/>Poets <hi>Canis a corio nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam abſter rebitur vncto,</hi> a cur cannot bee whipt from the Curriers greaſe-box, lo lie knawing in a chimney corner of ſome Moneſtery or Abby (ſweeete bones) then like painful hounds to be regarded, &amp; eſteemed for their skil in ſenting and laborious following and proſecuting of any commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable practiſe, and courſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
               <p>And ſurely I am verily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that neither the touch of conſcience, nor the ſenſe &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of any religion, euer drewe theſe into that damnable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twineable traine and owſell of perdition,<note place="margin">Idlenes and vnlavvfull ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures dravv many to that vvicked courſe of life, and the profeſſion of being Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> but onely a pleaſing humour of delighting their ſenſes with vaine and forraine faſhions, mixt with a moſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12920:44"/>reſolution, to ſticke on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that cuſtome and habit of life, which they had found moſt repleat, with oylie, ſluggiſh, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticall ſecuritie.<note place="margin">Diſcontent &amp; ouer-weening conceit of wit vndoes many a worthy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> The other ſort are drawne out of this land and her obedinence, or with pleaſing ſhews (for they wel ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtinguiſh ſhewes from ſubſtance) but with a prophane and enuious diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, to ſee ſome others (not ſo wiſe in their conceits, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) mounted vp to the ſeat of honour and preferment about the ſtate; for being not able tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough rancord malice and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of heart, contracted and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by miſconceite of their own worth and learning, in affaires of the ſtate,<note place="margin">The miſchiefe of enuie.</note> to ſubdue the inſurging affects &amp; inundations of pride, to that order and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience as may make their good
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12920:44"/>partes ſeruiceable to men of higher place, and by degrees mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter occaſions by their dutifull and painfull endeauours of their promotion &amp; dignitie, they will and muſt needs trauaile (becauſe <hi>Nemo Propheta in patria</hi> noe prieſt is long regarded (as they ſay) in his owne pulpit) to the popes grace, that onely roiall M. and ſoueraigne lord &amp; maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of learning, and learned, wiſe, politicke artiſts. And wil it pleaſe you in one view to ſee what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment and reckoning this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til painted ſheath of ſcholler-like promotions beſtoweth on ſuch his followers as goe out of this Gods grace, into that warm ſun? The acount ſurely that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had of <hi>Rhimerales,</hi> for <hi>Proditionem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo proditores odi</hi> is the popes poſie and poſition concerning Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12920:45"/>ſtarters, from their loyall and naturall faith &amp; alleagiance: hee loues the Pies tales,<note place="margin">Trecherie lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but the betrayers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> but the Pye is moſt bitter, diſtaſtful &amp; vnſauo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie. And therefore hee regardeth them as men doe poyſonous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, which they ſhoot at their enemies.<note place="margin">Traitors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded of their Maiſters as poyſonous Arrovves.</note> If the arrowes hit the partie they are ſhot at, they ſhall be ſurely broken, if they hit ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtanding by, they ſhall bee ſurely broken: if they hit not the body but light on the cloake or hat of him they are ſhot at, they ſhall bee ſurely broken: (vnleſſe happilye they light vppon ſuch a foole as ſometimes is reported when hee was ſtrooken through the noſe, to haue puld out the mans Arrowe patientlye, and by the way of priuate counſell, to haue told him in his eare, that if he ſhot ſo againe, he wold break
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12920:45"/>his Arrow) but they meete with no ſuch noſes of waxe as will be ſo ieſted with all; for the verye ayming with their venemous and irrilegious purpoſes &amp; plots, at the States heart and peaceable gouernment, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them open to vtter brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: and though they neuer hit (as I truſt none of that abhorred, vnnatural, &amp; diabolical crew ſhal euer hit ſo faire a white) their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intent and purpoſe expoſeth them to moſte milde and iuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Wil you ſee yet further the account is had of them by the Pope,<note place="margin">The pope a falſe dice-play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, vvith our poore coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimens liues.</note> the ſame that deboſt Gamſters &amp; deceitfull dice-play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, haue of yong nouices newly come to their lands: they drawe them in with a ſupper or two, let them win for their better incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement three or foure bowtes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12920:46"/>of ſmal worth, &amp; ſuddenly when they finde that they are through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tickled and pleaſed with their nibling ſucceſſe, they let downe the mouſe-trappe, cog in two or three falſe and vnlawfull Dice, &amp; wipe their yong gallant of all his golde, and ſend him like <hi>Aristip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> his golden ſheep either to ſome Iaſons fleece, or deſperat enterpriſe, or home into their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try to vnfleece his poor tenants for a new ſupply: In like maner deleth the pope with their liues, as the falſe Gamſters deale with young gamſters golde; giue them pleaſing content for a time but with a purpoſe to make them by deſperate aduenture game a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their deareſt blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Medeas</hi> Goulden Fleece is fayned by the poets to haue giuen many worthy and heroick ſpirits, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12920:46"/>to adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture to their deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as being kept by Gyants, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erie dragons, &amp; ſuch like horrid monſters, as may more at large in their poetical fictions appeare but our Engliſh true Golden-Fleece, hath cauſed the popes to ſend ouer more fooliſh hardy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers to the Stigian Lake of perdition; &amp; yet could neuer get one locke of it through all their deuiſes and demonical attempts. And can they thinke whome hee vſeth in ſo deſperate and vnlikely aduentures, that they are regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Pope their M a. when hee ſendeth them to fight with Lyons, and death-ſpitting Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons (for ſuch are, as euery childe doth note) the ſupporters of the peace &amp; tranquilitie of england) nay, with the Lyon of the houſe of IVDA who hath ſo taken
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12920:47"/>into his protection and defence, both the heart and the head of this ſtates welfare, with all her ſweete and princely branches (which God for euer proſper &amp; eſtabliſh) as if legions of deuils and deuiliſh ſpirits ſhould dayly ſeeke to ouerthrowe them, they ſhould not be able to pull one lock, nay to hurt one haire of her flouriſhing &amp; peace maintaining Solomon, or any of his moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious &amp; al religious hearts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting-ſeed and iſſue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The popes pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards our countrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men when they are han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for treaſon</note>Will you ſee yet further the regard is had of them by the Pope? they are trained vp &amp; nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed (as was noted before) as dogs, to make him ſporte by putting them vpon Lyons, and when their skins are puld ouer their eares by the tallents of vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12920:47"/>lawes and Iuſtice of the ſtate, hee gets (like a woman with childe of two twins, laughter for the fall of them, whome he fedde and fatted but to the ſhambles, and diſdaine for their il ſucceſſe) into his growning chayre, and pittieth them, thus:</p>
               <p>I ſent not for theſe Engliſh flies, their ſeruice was vnſought for, and ſought for onely as flies ſeeke after bloody meate; &amp; now if they haue met with the butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers flap, <hi>Tomeris</hi> his rewarde is iuſtly-falne vpon them: <hi>ſanguine ſatiantur qui ſanguinem ſitierunt:</hi> they greedilye hunted after a ſhamefull ſeruice, and they are paide with the wages of a ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ignominious death and deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like words haue
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12920:48"/>beene noted to haue proceeded vpon the death and hanging of many of our Roomes deereſt children, from the mouthes of thoſe blood-ſucking antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an tiraunts: Will you ſee yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (for I would gladly reclaime my deere countrimen that haue entered into that exorbitant courſe the very Pinfould of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers (and deterre all others from entertayning the like diſcontents &amp; ſeducements by vnmasking &amp; laying open the fruits &amp; aſſured profits may be expected to ariſe to any of that ſect) the beſt regard is had of them by the Pope,<note place="margin">The pope v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th Engliſh Seminaries as Curtizans do their loues.</note> euen the ſame that curtizans haue of young prodigals, who ſo long as their purſes are filled with duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and ſpur-royalls, ſhall want no royall entertainement, are
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12920:48"/>made ducklings at their lips and laps; kiſſed, imbraced, fed with all amorous muſicall ſweet varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of pleaſures, and inchanting delights, <hi>Vbi caeperint eſse invtiles, eijciuntur foras,</hi> when they haue ſpent all, ſtand behinde the dore for a cipher or warning peece; &amp; not onely ſo, but vpon the leaſt diſpleſure, are thruſt out of dores al betatterd and forlorne in their eſtates, ſmotherd not with kiſſes but with griefe, and beſmeared with ſhamefull reproaches, and diſdainefull tearmes, in ſtead of ſugered and hony ſalutations: ſo theſe whileſt their heads are full fraughted with da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable plots &amp; practiſes to aduance the Popes ſupremacy &amp; regallity, they ſhall want neither gould nor goulden words: nothing can be too deare
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12920:49"/>or to daintye for them, till they are thruſt into deathes ſnare: but if they miſſe of their wicked and vnchriſtian like purpoſes, (as they haue euer hetherto prayſed be the keeper of Iſrael, and euer ſhall while Iſrael prayſeth the protector of <hi>Iaccobs</hi> houſe) their accounts ſhal be at their returne (if euer they doe returne) as of olde and ouer-ſpent horſes tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to graze in ſome pennurious paſture for breede and trayning vp of others to the like offices, who if they boldlye attempt and be intercepted of their moſte ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable and helliſh vndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning treaſons, they meete with Dyricks diet,<note place="margin">Dirickes dyet prepared for Traytors.</note> a bitter Cup prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſtilled out of the venefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hearbs of their owne, either vnſetled, or diſcontented and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12920:49"/>braines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obiections fondly made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the death of Semi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naries.</note>And heere I muſt needes take occaſion to anſwere the fond &amp; friuolous obiections that many idle &amp; troubleſome heads make concerning the death of Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Ieſuites, caſting out, that they dye for the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, and their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake, therby taxing the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this ſtate, &amp; the late queenes rigor, and the ſeueritie of ſome, eſpeciallye that moſte religious pillar of Gods truth, the now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L. B.</hi> The papiſts tearme our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion a newe found &amp; Cecil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lian Religion: becauſe that worthy Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor vnder the late Queene was a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſame</note> wiſe and worthy Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of this ſtate, tearming the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which we vnder her grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and ſoules-releeuing go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment profeſſed, a new found and Cecillian religion (O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie title, a title that wil be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the regiſter of eternal me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12920:50"/>
                  <hi>aere plus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adamantino</hi> to his, and his poſterities euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fame.</p>
               <p>True it is which fewe doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue or rightly vnderſtand (for to reaſon of the antiquitie of our religion,<note place="margin">The reaſon why the lawe take; the goods &amp; part of the lands from Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants.</note> is neither befitting my function nor ſcope) that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why any lawe was enacted, to take from recuſants their goods, and 2-parts of their lands, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it ſelfe from this palpable proofe, that Recuſants were not contented to inioy the liberty of their religion and conſcience, but moſt of them became bye Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries and Maſſe-prieſts (ſent ouer by their Cayphardicall M. to breed ſedition and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of this Realmes peace and quiet) reuolters in heart from their ſoueraigne alleagiance, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12920:50"/>were indeede flatly reconciled to the Pope and his iuriſdiction, and ſupremacie.</p>
               <p>For the Romiſh Churche houlde an opinion,<note place="margin">The opinion of the Church of Rome tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement to the pope.</note> that for a Catholike (as they terme them) to come to Churche before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement to the Pope, was but Sciſmaticall, but to come to Church and to be intermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with vs in deuine ſeruice &amp; participating of the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, after reconciliation to the Pope, and his ſupremacie, (and to be ſo reconciled to the Pope) what is it by their owne teſtimonie, but preferring the popes authoritie before their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall princes (which is treaſon in the higheſt degree) was plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hereticall, damnable, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnpardonable; whereupon
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12920:51"/>the wiſdome of the ſtate at that time (for <hi>huic illae lachrymae,</hi> the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Cecillian Religion came) perceauing, that howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by the priuate &amp; ſecret abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Ieſuit &amp; houſe prieſt, it could not bee challingingly prooued and euicted, that they which refrayned our Church, were reconciled to the Pope, and renounced her Maieſtis pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſupreame authoritie, yet <hi>ex conſequenti</hi> it was as cleere as light at noone day, that all they which obſtinatelye refuſed the holy communion and deuine ſeruice, were directly reconciled to the Pope. And therfore her Maieſtie (as now our gratious &amp; deare Lord and Soueraigne ſtands affected) loth to ſhed the blood of ſo many ſubiects, held it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12920:51"/>ſit in policie for the better and ſafer preſeruation of this Realm in peace and tranquilitie, onelye to curbe and keepe downe Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants from growing mightie, powerfull, and rich (being inteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine ill willers to his royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and imperial ſtate and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) by the depriuation of their goods and loſſe of part of their Landes: and like a wiſe and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Chyrurgian <hi>(vt metus ad omnes, animaduerſio adpau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniret)</hi> to cut off only the infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and poyſoning partes and members, which are theſe Ieſuits and Seminaries, the ſeducers of the peoples hearts not from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but from their naturall pyetie and ſoueraigne duetie &amp; allegiance. Now let it be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in equall ballance, whether
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12920:52"/>thoſe times and thoſe courſes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> held, or which now vnder his Maieſties flouriſhing &amp; ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (but more exceeding lye peaceable) gouernement, are held againſt Seminaries and Ieſuites, Sauour of crueltie or deſire of blood, or any other humour then a religious policie, to keep in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right tearmes, &amp; in perfect tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and tune, the ſweete harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of this ſtates happye regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And thus much ſhal ſuffice to haue ſpoken of Seminaries &amp; Ieſuites, wherin that I haue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what digreſſed, let no man mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, it ſtands within the cheefe ſcope of my ſubiect which is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, and this is one point of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, which is the moſt affected to Popery (for many of them are full of theſe kinde of obiections)
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12920:52"/>would duely obſerue, they would anſwer by this their own weake, wanton, and very womanniſh obiections, concerning theſe and the like caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:53"/>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:12920:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6. Concerning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectors.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Roiectors! why, what are they?<note place="margin">A Deſcription of proiectors.</note> I noted 2. ſortes of them: they are your onely, not onely politicians, but directers &amp; plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſtate-buſines (or rather continual makers of buſines, and trouble to the ſtate gouernours) without whome the ſtate cannot ſtand (or rather for whome the ſtate gouernours cannot ſtand or reſt in quiet.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:12920:54"/>
               <p>If you deſire to know them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they are ſuch as haue not like Philoſophers made a proiection of goulde, but caſte awaye their goulden thrifte and eſtates thorough ſome looſe and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect courſes; and to repaire it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, take the direct lineway to the court,<note place="margin">proiecters like fiſher-men-</note> like fiſhermen (becauſe they haue hard, there is no fiſhing to the Sea, nor ſeruice to the Court toicaſte about with their hookes and nettes for a newe goulden promiſed eſtate.</p>
               <p>If you deſire to knowe them further, they are Pedlers, or Pedling informers of the State, men that haue lapped vp from the vommit of other mens wits, ſome excrements of Court-phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and thereuppon turne Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors about the court &amp; contriue
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12920:54"/>Proiects and ſtrange deuiſes of tobaco-pipes, <hi>Cardas finas,</hi> brown paper, french wares, dunghill ſhrids, and a thouſand of the like conceites, to trouble the State withall, wherein they labour and trot vp &amp; down as buſily as Bees, carrying all the worlde in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, that they haue ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall imployments about the State, as will let them reſt neither night nor day.</p>
               <p>And truly they are right Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, for the trading to the Eaſt and Weſt Indies gets but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and their trading from their lodgings to the Court with a bundell of papers, and from the Courte to their Lodgings begets them, like Eaſt and Weſt voyages, a yearely, yea daylie reuennewe. For to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12920:55"/>the expectation of their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and happye ſucceſſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny healthes are drunk, and much good cheere dayly taſted: Their Mercer, their Taylor, their Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, their oſtes, their patients, are drawne by hoopes of their court aduentures, &amp; faire ſhewes and pretenſes to truſt and furniſh them with all neceſſaries, <hi>ad vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum et veſtitum,</hi> and are induced to let their fingers bee keyes of their coffers while all is ſpent; but when their patients and their Creditors through ouer-long deferring (for their proiects are like the houre Saturne, that fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth his courſe but once in three yeares, nay theſe ſcarce one of them thriue or come forward once in three liues) are rubde to the quicke; either a new nayle
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12920:55"/>muſt driue out the other, or elſe being known to be ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced and their proiects eiected as matters vnworthy to paſſe the Seates of graue Audience, much leſſe the ſeates of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, they ſpitefullye fret and fume, and in their ſecret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners mutter, that fewe or none of the ſtate were able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, or ſound to the depth of their proiects.</p>
               <p>Will you now know who are their retayners? Lice and Mice are ſaid by DIOGINES to be poore mens retainers &amp; followers,<note place="margin">Vaine &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectors Retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> but theſe haue lief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, captaines, caualiers, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the ſpruceſt ſtamp &amp; edition to attend them earelie and late, whereby the graue &amp; ponderous affaires &amp; buſines
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12920:56"/>of the ſtate is very intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly many times combred and tediouſly wronged.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of proiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, are ſuch as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſpoake of, but to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end; who were euer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards wiuing and yet mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, that were alwaies in a readines to ſaile on the ſea, and yet tooke no Shippe, that addreſſed themſelues to enter into the buſines of the common wealth, &amp; yet entred not into anye honeſt imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at all, that had prepared and framed (but like women <hi>dum moliunter et comuntur an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt,</hi> while they are a dreſſing and a drawing, one may ride to yorke) themſelues to be in the Court, and to liue in houſe-holde
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12920:56"/>with men of high State &amp; great power, and yet were loath forſooth to be tyed to ſubiection, &amp; daily attendance.</p>
               <p>And yet not-withſtanding they will be dayly Courtiers and Politicke directors too. For either they will frame &amp; apply themſelues, though in no wiſe to be daily attendants and ſeruants (for that's too groſſe, and too abhorring from the french ſtrayne) but to be followers and direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Tutors and Inſtructors of young noble-men, ſuch as are rawe and vntrained in the ſubtil courſes of this age, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring alwaies matters of pleaſures and delight to their pitchie aprehenſions, &amp; in that reſpect proue no better many
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12920:57"/>times then their panders, or if they cannot thriue ſo to their full content, they vulture-like ſeeke out the <hi>cadauera,</hi> and ceaze vpon the ſoares of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented nobles, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them leſſons &amp; precepts of more diſcontentment and enuie.</p>
               <p>And to gaine neerer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with them,<note place="margin">Dangerous &amp; miſchieuous proiectors</note> they will be euer feeding their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors with the pleaſing Syrene ſonges of their good parts, &amp; extraordinarie skill and dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in ſtate buſineſſe, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before them their admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red valours, their worthy and highly extolled-bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties, &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralities, and ſo by degrees draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the twine threds of their owne delights, (for
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12920:57"/>theſe proiectors are caſters of their netts, alwaies into trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled (waters) into an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaning conceite of their owne worthes, and vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and vndue regardes of other their equalls, honeſt, ſtudious, and faithfull ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors about the ſtates welfare, and neuer leaue, making them like Fiſh, catch at the baites of diſhonorable and ignoble miſconceiuings, till they are ſtrooke with the deadlye hookes of their owne, too to much, but ouer late pittyed and lamented deſtruction and ruine.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the verie viperous Phalangia and Cantherides of Nobilitie: The Phyloſophers called ſuch men <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12920:58"/>little puſhes and pimples of glory, and rightly: for as they through their continuall itch bred perpetuall vnreſt, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes to ſuch as were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with them, ſo doe theſe preceptors of vaine glory and diſcontent, beget in noble and free ſpirits nothing but an it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching humour of putting them forward to deſperate and Polipus-like practiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by their plotters, &amp; inſtructers but the ſtages and actors of their wickedly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, either malicious or vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious or ambitious purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and like puſhes they in the end prooue vnto them, for when they breake out into publique note and viewe, the filthe and matter of their long
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12920:58"/>harbored &amp; hidden hearts mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, runs about the vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; vnblemiſht faces of their fames, &amp; honor, and ſo infects them, that the ſcarres &amp; Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices thereof can hardly euer be ſalued &amp; healed vp againe: but I rather liken ſuch men to impoſtumes in the throat or ſtomack, which as experience teacheth vs, are not ſeene nor diſcerned, but take a man ſuddainely when the worlde thinkes all ſounde and healthfull within the party diſeaſed, and breake out in a moment, with ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of corruption, as diſpatcheth him before his friends, who ſtand all amazed at the ſuddaine miſchance, can conceaue which way to ſeeke
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12920:59"/>remedie, or what remedie to apply.</p>
               <p>So theſe harboring and ſetling by their falſe ſurmiſes, and crude and imperfect ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, within the ſtomackes and mawes of noble Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, corrupt impoſtumes of enuy and rancoure, applye flegmaticke matter and dayly formentall exaſperations of indiſgeſted miſpriſions, and vnkinde aſperſions, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuffered to feede within them to a ripenes, breake forth ſuddainely into ſuch diſorder, (euen when all is thought ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the coare of their firme and faithfull allegiance) as irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerably caſteth them away, &amp; leaues their friends, to vtter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazedneſſe and diſcomfort.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12920:59"/>
                  <hi>Hos tu Romane caueto,</hi> God keepe all true and Noble hearts from ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectors, plotters &amp; Politicians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:60"/>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:12920:60"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7. Concerning ſubſtan tiall States-men.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are many can talk very free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of incountring with Lyons, and wraſtling with Beares, who dare looke neither in the face. And as many that vainely will predicate and boaſt of great learning and vnderſtanding in the deepeſt affaires of the State, who can not guide the Triremes much leſſe the Quinquiremes of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12920:61"/>of any weightie imployment. The ouerweening conceite whereof, maketh ſome who haue read ouer a peece of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles politicks, to deeme it no vſurpation, to aſcribe vnto themſelues the title of Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians. And if they haue turned ouer ſome few leaues of ISO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRATES ſhort precepts, or but 4 ſides of SEXTVS IVLIVS FRON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TINVS, his foure bookes of Stratagems, <hi>ſupercilioſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hunt frontem,</hi> They caſt their heads ouer the left ſhoulder, they thinke themſelues ſeated and enthroaned in the breſt of MINERVA, bred in APPOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LO his braines, and able to mannage any publike affaires: verie ſubſtantiall Stateſ-men.</p>
               <p>But little doe they know what deepe and ſecret miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12920:61"/>are to be found in Court-learning, and how different from Schoole tearmes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt court learning and Schoole-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>Schollers in their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are all of them to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced &amp; reſpected in their ſeuerall degrees of excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, yet they muſt vnderſtand that they who wade into the depth of generallities, cannot be fit inſtruments of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler imployments, eſpeciallye concerning worldlye affaires, much leſſe the occaſions and occurrence; of the common-wealth. For although in the Theoricke they vnderſtand, &amp; can out of their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſcourſe at full, many of them, of many things that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in their printed Authors touching Peace and Warre,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12920:62"/>yet the want of experience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth them of that fitnes and agilitie in the performance of thoſe matters, which to ſome by a ſecret inſtinct of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, helpt with continuall practiſe, comes ſo ready, as when they are conuerſant in ſtate-imployments, ſeeme to be like fiſh in the Sea, <hi>In loco proprio,</hi> as contrary wiſe meere profeſt ſchollers admitted to any courtly function,<note place="margin">Why meere profeſt ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are not fit for publique action and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</note> about a Prince and his ſtate, bewray moſt of them a ſheepiſh ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, the beſt of them a want of ſpirit and dexteritie, which addes to all actions in euerie outward profeſſion ſuch a grace, as they who are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any publique deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without it, ſeeme but
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12920:62"/>
                  <hi>Sutores vltra crepidam:</hi> and I muſt make bould to ſay (thogh I wiſh aſwell to letters and the Muſes as any vnlearned well-willer of them can) that if Princes in their behauiours &amp; cauſes politicke, ſhould ſtand to ſchoole arguments,<note place="margin">Princes beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours &amp; acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon lawes, not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</note> order (the ſtrict obſeruation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of makes a Prince moſte emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, eſpecially in his courte) would often times beg at his gates and wander like a baniſht vagabond.</p>
               <p>For howſoeuer the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of court and common-wealth came from the rules of philoſophie, &amp; to them muſt indeed refer their offpring, yet becauſe the treaties of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers conſiſt in a generall conſideration of thinges, they
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12920:63"/>leaue to euerie one that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them a ſcope of his owne opinion and interpretation, whereas the Lawes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler obſeruations confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and eſtabliſhed in either court or the vniuerſall ſtate, make them ceaſe as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall diſcourſes to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged opinitiuely tru or falſe, for they ſet downe poſitiuely this is granted and approoued by generall conſent of the wiſeſt and profoundeſt Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts good or badde, and ſo fouldes vs within aſſured boundes, which if wee might paſſe in breach, as ſchollers turne them vp and downe in the vncertaintie of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions &amp; argumentations, our natures would range infinitely
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12920:63"/>into all enormities, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders.</p>
               <p>Princes affaires muſt not be ordered by a free diſcourſe of reaſon, but the gouernment of their eſtates muſt bee tyed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the cuſtomes, Lawes, &amp; municipall ſtatutes of their countries already eſtabliſhed &amp; ratified; or to the profound and diſcerning iudgement of diſcreete, wiſe, and experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced rulers, which being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they whoſe skill conſiſts more in what they haue read, then what they haue with a digeſted Iudgement obſerued conuenient for euerie functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and office of publique go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, cannot bee reputed fit for the managing of Court buſineſſe, beeing indeede de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12920:64"/>of the chiefeſt helpe of their ſeuerall imployments, which is a iudgement preſt &amp; alwaies prouided, diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhingly to order, ſettle and diſpoſe all affaires and occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of a State, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in him that is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally incombred, and enfolded within the multiplicitie of contemplatiue ſtudies.</p>
               <p>For though varietie of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and turning ouer many learned authors, is a great help to all other ſcholer-like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; as diuinitie,<note place="margin">Socrates his opinion of booke lerning how hurtfull to the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of great ſtateſmen.</note> phiſicke, law, yet nothing hinders more a ſtates-mans attaining of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the skil &amp; miſtery of ſtate-learning, then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding himſelfe &amp; his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with multifarious intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenes
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12920:64"/>of book co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits: for if the light of iudgement (which in all concluſions and negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, is moſt preualent) bee inueloped &amp; inclouded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the miſts of many diuerſe, ſcatterd &amp; vncollected opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and opinitiue ſaies &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, what can it publiquely produce, or performe worthy the repute of a perfect and all ſufficient Statiſt? I doe not exclude all Schollers from the buſines and affaires of the State, but my reaſon chiefely importeth, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man who is well ſeene in STRATAGEMICALL diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, and the ſtudy of State-learning, may not think that ſufficient to inable him in the excecution of publique
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12920:65"/>affaires, but an exact exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation muſt bee had of the ſtrength and abilitie of his iudgement, who intendeth to applie himſelfe to graue and weightie cauſes in anye pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique function and duetie, for ſurely it cannot bee imagined that any man who is not moſt plentifullie inritched,<note place="margin">A diſcerning iudgement. principally to be required in a ſtates-man.</note> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with this moſte vnualua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſure of a diſcerning, obſeruing and applying iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment (which ſeldom poſſeſſeth men ouer-buſied and out-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited in contemplatiue ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) can bee fitte for the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and negotiating in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affaires of the common-wealth.</p>
               <p>For, as DEMOSTHENES ſaide of pronountiation in an
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:12920:65"/>Oratour, ſo may I ſay in a Stateſ-man, that iudgement is the firſt, the ſecond, and the laſt, yea all in all requiſite, without which no man, neuer ſo well ſeene either in booke-learning, or obſeruations in any publique buſines, can be able to proue excellent, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fit to rule the Horſes of the ſun, or pull in and let out, as the neceſſitie and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doe require, the raines of any ſtate gouernment.<note place="margin">Manye by the verie helpe of nature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any greate inſight of Schoole-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, haue prooued throughout all ages woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Stateſ-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>There haue bene many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all ſtates, euen by the inſtinct and helpe of Nature and experience, to haue proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued moſt excellent and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy common-wealths-men, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing had ſmall or little furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of booke learning.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:12920:66"/>
               <p>And queſtionleſſe a man may well applying himſelfe to the ſtudy of State-affaires, be fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered by conuerſing &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Hiſtoricall and Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagemicall ſtudies, that hath an excellent witte and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to applye and make vſe of the ſame in his particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, without much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of time; but it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for anye Man, neuer ſo much backed with the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of politicke Authors, without this ſpeciall guift of iudgement, in obſeruing eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fit &amp; conuenient Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, touching his ſeuerall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, to prooue excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the ſtudy &amp; profeſſion of perfect State-knowledge: and whoſoeuer ſhall bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſtate imployments
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12920:66"/>rawly vpon booke rules, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out long experience &amp; obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, ſhall be found to ſinck vnder the burden of their deep vndertakinges, &amp; make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues &amp; their liues both a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſlauery &amp; vexation, &amp; a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual mockery &amp; ſcorne. For like raſh and headdy cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines imployments (that may be ſaid rather <hi>curſibus quam vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriis nationes peragrare,</hi> courſe through, rather then conquer many nations) ſo will all their actions appeare, &amp; be approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to the wiſeſt &amp; experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedſt Statiſts moſt ſlightly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. For how is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that intendeth to learne &amp; draw out the ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any countrye, to take a perfect and exact deſcription of the particulers, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king certaine ſuddaine ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12920:67"/>ſleight &amp; curſory notes of the ſame? no man of ſenſe or iudgement doth conceaue it poſſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What to bee conſidered in plotting, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, and ſetting foorth ſeuerall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and ſoiles</note>For there is required to the exact Coſmography of any country, a due and careful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of many perticulars in perticulars, which cannot be had by running, but by walking ſtayedly and ſteadily throughout, and by reſting &amp; reſiding ſometimes, thereby to gather and diſtinguiſh to his conceit the ſeuerall groues, the Paludes, the vallies, the mountaines, the campeſtrian and ſilueſtrian ſoiles and ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations. No more is it poſſible for any man to prooue an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Map-man, in the perfect skill and vnderſtanding of the ſeuerall affaires of any State,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12920:67"/>except by the penſil of his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation and experience, he haue chauked &amp; pointed out the mountanous occurrences, of and concerning the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; nobles behauiours, the vallies of the peoples orders, and diſorders, with fit preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and aduiſements con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all, both Silueſtrian, and Campeſtrian, rurall, and vrbane occaſions, as alſo haue a full and generall inſight, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the particular veines and mines, as it were of forraine and hom-bred cuſtomes and commodities.</p>
               <p>And who can recollect and draw all theſe accidents and a thouſand more, properlye and moſt neceſſarily belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to a perfect &amp; compleat
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12920:68"/>ſubſtantial Stateſ-mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to their ſeueral lines and places, without an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarye reach and applying iudgement, which muſt be the hand to direct the penſill of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie neceſſarie and fit occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. It is the heat of cleere and pure burning iudgement, which like fire ſeuereth &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth vpon all occaſions the droſſe from the pure golde, which diſtinguiſheth ſolide pearles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liquid haile-ſtones, manacles from bracelets, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines of incombrance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring deſignements from imployments full of honour, credit, ſafetie, and reputation. It is iudgement, which maketh a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admitted to the ſtate ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely powerfull, like a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12920:68"/>Phiſition, inſtructed with al maner of perfect skil, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a ſoueraigne and precious ſalue, to euery particular ſore of the common-wealth. This diſcerning iudgement, will teach and inſtruct him infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye that hath obtained the ſame, how to behaue himſelfe in all the courſes and affayres of his life, in ſuch ſort, as hee ſhall moſte eaſilye diſtinguiſh errors from truth, and deuide that which is profitable and conuenient from that which is hurtfull and offenſiue to his future and preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p>This will enforme him, when all ſchoole-points will faile him (like falſe friendes in aduerſitie) how to beare
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12920:69"/>himſelf in the moſt dangerous &amp; doubtful times, that his life ſhalbe ſubiect vnto.<note place="margin">Good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of Philoſophers, neceſſarie rules for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For although good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of wiſe men, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned inſtructions of philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, are firme grounds to ſet a ciuill man in the right way, for his ordinary conuerſation, and the directions of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Politicians may verye well, (by adding thereunto his owne wary obſeruations) point out a fit and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent behauiour for al ſorts of people, and which in geſture, ſpeeche, and outward graces and complements, may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently warrant his cariage to Prince, to Parents, to friends, to ſeruants, to ſuperiours, to inferiours, yet let him knowe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12920:69"/>if euer he ſhall be admitted to the managing many doubtful &amp; ſcrupulous points of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſtate, wherin ſhall depend either the ruin or the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the weale publique, or if not ſo, a great rent or ſtroak may be giuen by ill aduiſe, as contrarywiſe a great heape of honour may ariſe to himſelfe, and good to the common-wealth, by wiſe and well ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding counſell, therein to haue a cleere iudgement, far ſurpaſſing all others, wherby he may be able to vnderſtand, of many courſes, which (acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuerſitie of many mens opinions) ſhalbe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded: which is not onely the likelieſt, but certainely the beſt, argues not a man wel red
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12920:70"/>in books, or ſtudiouſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in other mens directions, and obſeruations, (for many accidents fall out and are offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the conſideration of a man occupied in the deep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of the common-wealth whereof he ſhall finde no likelihood of example, or pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to cut out his preſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by) but a ſingular emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie of wit and iudgement, diuinely inſpired from God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. And whoſoeuer can be able to caſt, not onely an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight but an inſight into the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hauiour and cariage of ſuch a man, vppon whome God hath beſtowed this diſcerning and all-deuiding iudgement, his ſeuerall actions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſhall not ſeeme to him
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12920:70"/>actions ſmelling of lanthorne and candle, or ſauouring of learned authors &amp; diſcourſes (for many, yea moſt who can ſay much more (as I noa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) out of ancient hiſtories &amp; booke-obſeruations, often ſee leſſe in diiudicating perticular ſtate-caſes) but the behauiours reſpects &amp; cariages of a man through his quicke and Eagle-like-ſight of iudgement, firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolued in al doubtful cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to ſticke to one courſe: for that is the very life of al State-wiſedome, ſuddainely and in a trice, to attaine to a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in al determinations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. For many are in ſhewe very wiſe, in confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence very profound, in maters of difference very acute &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12920:71"/>banding to and froe now one reaſon, then an other, and thoſe very plauſible and likely, but for want of this iudgement or rather iudicious reſolution (which in a ſtatesman hath the prime and principall ſeat, when ſentence definitiuely is to be pronounced, cannot ſo eaſily ſticke to one courſe and proiect, as finde out many.</p>
               <p>And yet many of theſe nimble-headed and quicke-conceited wiſemen, (which I neuer maruell at, becauſe I knowe by experience that the greateſt hindrance to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect wiſedome is to be puffed vp with a high conceit of ones owne wit and proper vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) hauing inflamed braines and heated imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:12920:71"/>to a promptnes and volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of ſpeach, account, in reſpect of themſelues, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fooles: ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeemes to them the lightning (for I cannot call it light) of their wit and reaſoning (for I cannot call it reaſon and iudgement) and halfe drunken facultie of belching out at their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries &amp; pots, ordinarie &amp; triui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conceits: and happily (that I may giue the beſt of them ſome reſpect) for the inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many plots and ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, theſe hot braines, are far excellenter, then iudicious and deepe reaching and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Statiſts, but when they come to the execution of weighty cauſes: ſuch as may either helpe or hinder them
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:12920:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>for euer, either in publike or their owne priuate negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuch a dizineſſe, and dim darneſſe ouer-ſhadowes the true light of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (which is by them ſildom exerciſed) as you may obſerue them (like birds in Snow) fall when the Sunne is at the higheſt of his ſtrength, into moſte apparant dangers, and run with fierce ſpeede into their aduerſaries nets. And thus much may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wel of the painted profeſſors of State-learning, as of the true and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect Statiſtes of any religious common-wealth, with their ſeueral habits, ſhewes, offices, &amp; diſtinctiue faculties, wherin if (according to the little skill and perſpection, which by
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12920:72"/>God and nature is infuſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my vnderſtanding) I haue ſhott neare the marke of your content, my content and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſuperaboundeth.</p>
               <p>Howſoeuer, the errors I haue committed you muſt attribute to my diſtractions, the fruites of a weak &amp; ſicke body, which according to the rules of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, many times alter the temperature of the minde, &amp; where any thing dooth either <hi>deeſse in neceſſariis,</hi> or <hi>abundare in ſuperfluis,</hi> want in matter or abound in forme, you muſt ſupplye with the ſwift winges of your loue, the defects of the one, &amp; prune of, with the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful knife of your diſcretion &amp; applicatorye iudgement, the ſarmenting &amp; ouer-ſpreading boughes of the other.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:12920:73"/>
               <p>With theſe I commend my loue to your louing entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wiſhing that (although they are but Pans-reade and rurall-ſonges, they might (as matters ſet downe by the pen of APOLLO) ſound ſweetlye in your apprehenſion, &amp; giue to your conceite moſt conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting muſicke, pleaſure, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               <p>In my next (ſo you ſhall bee pleſed to accept theſe in good worth) I wil ſtreine the ſtrings of my beſt witts, to giue you a reliſh of ſweeter harmony.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Philodeſpolus. <hi>I. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:73"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:74"/>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:12920:74"/>
            <head>A Sixe-fold precept, of Pollicie.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>NEARCHVS to his PHILO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DESPOLVS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your hands the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſt of your appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued loue, your ſixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foulde diſcouerie of Pollicye, wherebye I haue conceiued both <hi>plauſtrum lubentiarum,</hi> a carrefull of pleaſing, and yet moſte true and vncontrowlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſuch vanities and abſurdities as are hourely practiſed in the courſe of the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12920:75"/>world, and march vnder the Silken Banner of outwardlye profeſſed Tytles of vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie friuolous, or malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie turbulent Politicians; And in your ſixt and laſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie fullye perceiued your iudgement in ſetting downe, (bee it ſpoken without flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) ſuch exact, perpended, and ponderous deſcriptions of perfect Pollicye and State-learning, as was not expected from your Pen. <hi>Veterem feren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Inturiam, inuitas nouam:</hi> The pleaſure and profit I haue drawne from your precedent Politique diſcourſes, embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth mee to inioyne you to a new trouble, before I haue giuen you anye content or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment for your former ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12920:75"/>courteſies.</p>
               <p>Your pen hath led my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit into a groue or thicket of many vſe-ful but generall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, but if you leaue my tender yeares, without your <hi>Ariadnes</hi> thred of conduction, your loue will prooue wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſtraction, and an expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of my vnſetled thoughts, to the wilde beaſts of diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. Therefore I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your louing Conuoy, for the ſetling me in the ſafe and plaine way of ſome particular precepts: and as you haue ſet downe the ground worke of a true and perfect States-man, as alſo the <hi>Cyclopaedia</hi> which moſt powerfully ruleth and muſt be made the chiefe and principall workeman in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12920:76"/>all affaires of ciuil &amp; politicke gouernment, by him which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to be regarded for his wiſe carriage in any religious common-wealth: ſo you wold take paines to ad to thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral propoſitions, ſome fewe particular precepts, which as ſea-markes may inable mee in this infidelious age, to ſhun &amp; auoid ſuch rocks &amp; quick-sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of treachery &amp; deceipt, as high fortunes &amp; eſtats are ordinary ſubiect vnto.</p>
               <p>For like as ſuch perſons as haue to do in the game &amp; feat of wraſtling, haue in a redines certaine ſure pointes &amp; waies both to catch hold, &amp; alſo to winde out of their aduerſaries foyle &amp; grapple: ſo muſt they who intend to trauel in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines &amp; occupations of peace
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12920:76"/>&amp; war, of neceſſity haue in rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dines (according to <hi>Eraſm.</hi> his admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ſure rules, by which they may be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance what is in manye doubtfull particular caſes, needefull to be don, or omitted, Shew ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore without any ſubterfugie, your ability &amp; propenſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, go giue ſatisfaction to this my requeſt.</p>
               <p>You ſhall adde heereby to mine &amp; other my good frends opinions now had of your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in politicke obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, a large and locuplete increaſe of your repute, and ſhewe mee an infallible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; conſignation of your vndoubted loue, and laſtlye ſet vpon the Talley of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and Loue, ſuch debtes
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12920:77"/>of your deſeruinges, as ſhall make me carefully ſtudious &amp; ſtudiouſlye carefull to repay them with treble ſatisfaction and remuneration.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your louing Nearchus. <hi>C. S.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:12920:77"/>
               <head>PHILODESPO VS his anſwere to <hi>Nae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archus</hi> his requeſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued (dear ſir) was your owne. For whatſoeuer guiftes of arte or nature weare my inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are by adoption your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations, for I haue long ſince in heart bequeathed and deſigned al the faculties of my minde and abilitie of bodye to your commaund and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12920:78"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>I haue wiped away from the Table of my remembrance all formes and effigies, that firſt, middle and laſt, at all times, &amp; aboue all thinges I might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe freſh in my memorie your faithfull fauours, ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and ſo freelye expended vppon mee, a man of ſo little worth and reſpect. If any thing in thoſe weake iudgements, proceeding from weakeneſſe it ſelfe euery waies, did ſit ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at your heart, &amp; conveyed to your thoughts either plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or profit, I care not what diſpleaſure or diſeaſeful vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et they brought vpon me. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your requeſt, it was <hi>Brut.</hi> his ſaying (as Plutarche in his liues maketh mention) that it argned a great want of wit,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:12920:78"/>not to bee able to denye anye thing requeſted. And ſurelye though their breatheth not on earth that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that might leaue me ſooner void of wit or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to deny or excuſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you ſhold by requeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund (for I haue euer accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your requeſts, as powerfull and abſolute commaundes) yet <hi>lupum auribus teneo,</hi> through this your motion I am driuen into ſuch commotion, as my ſickneſſe more diſquieteth not my body, then this demurr &amp; dependance diſordereth my thoghts. To deny you, the ſenſe of gratitude, of ciuility, debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me; to yeeld, the weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the impoſure, a burden which I am no way able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge with anye warrantable account of credit, and the qualitye of the ſuite, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12920:79"/>buſineſſe propounded, vtterly deterres me.</p>
               <p>For to take vppon mee to point out particlar leſſons, &amp; inſtructions, ſuch as may bee directors to a man of that ſtate and fortunes, (as both by your noble order and rank, and much more by your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and ſtudye in liberall Artes and faculties of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt miſteries of learning, is likelye, and altogether ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and expected to bee deriued vppon you) were to note out a Caeſar-like ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in my thoughts and would certainely lay my folly and weakeneſſe open to much ſcorne and deriſion.</p>
               <p>And againe, (beloued Sir) the gouernment of a publike
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12920:79"/>State, you muſt conſider is like to a ſhip at ſea, continualy toſſed with vncertaine waues and ſurgees, euen as the more vncertaine windes and State-tempeſts of ſudain mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and accidentall alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diuulſions daily ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing one in the necke of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhall affect it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ſure or certaine direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can be prefixed and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to drawe the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar lines of a ſtates-mans life and actions by, your owne daily obſeruations, when you ſhall be admitted to action, wilbe ſurer and perfecter Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptors vnto you, then any the moſt experienced ſtates-mans rules and precepts: and from me, how can you thinke (being
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:12920:80"/>neuer admitted to the practiue part of policie &amp; publique go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement) that any note of worth or regard can be drawn? therefore I pray you vnbend the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of this your requeſt which I know was made by you with no other purpoſe then to try &amp; feele the forwardnes of my inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leaſt ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a raſh and precipitate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion of weightier vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, then either my abilitie could beare vp and ſupport, or the fitnes and congruitie of this function &amp; performance beare out, you ſhall (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) if heerein I haue not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied you (as I truſt I haue) at my next meeting and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, be with more ſurchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging reaſons ſufficiently reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12920:80"/>to content touching your requeſt. In the meane time I will thinke of ſomething more fitting, and I hope as fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorie, which I may offer as an appeaſing ſacrifice to your conſideration, and ſo for this time I commend your diligent and Bee-like ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to Gods all proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering fauour and bleſſings.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours not as hee would but as hee may <hi>I. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:81"/>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:12920:81"/>
               <head>Naearchus, his reply.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood friend (by the name of frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and ſeruant both I kindely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure you) that you would not vſe me as <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronius Thurinus</hi> vſed <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seuerus</hi> his poore ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, to ſmother me with lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring excuſes and delaies, nor make vſe of your wit in putting off and declining the force of my moſt neceſſarie requeſts. What <hi>Brutus</hi> his conceit was, concernes not
<pb facs="tcp:12920:82"/>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:12920:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:12920:83"/>particular; you ſhall by your denialls but ſet me into more longing, and with more forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble purſuite, make me to arie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; preſſe forward woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like againſt al obiected allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In this one concluſion I will drowne al your doubtes and demurres, your weakenes and imbicilitie (if it ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any errors) ſhalbe poyzed within the ballance of my loue and kinde acceptance, and within the curtaines of moſt booſome ſecreſie, ſhall they be intombed. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I cannot deny but that when dangerous tempeſts ſud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dainely ariſe at Sea, prayer &amp; reſolution to death is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable, &amp; that in a tempeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſtate, where all thinges
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12920:83"/>are continually in an vprore, &amp; diſorderly confuſed, throgh daily and inteſtine warre, poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke precepts doe as little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, as aſtronomicall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations at ſea, in rough, and all skill-drowning ſtormes: yet it were madnes for men that are to trauel by ſea, vtterly to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the due &amp; exact obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſeueral ſands, gulffes, cliffes, rockes, reatches, and ſhoares; ſo were it a plaine madnes, for him that endeauoreth to paſſe through the ſtreights and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of deep and dangerous imployments, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend his actions to the winde, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of euery accident, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any due and diligent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration what he acteth, or which way his purpoſes
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:12920:84"/>ſhall ariue at their propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ends, and be crowned with his deſired and expected reſpects.</p>
               <p>For certainely in the moſt troubleſome confuſion of tempeſts, though a good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and reſolution hath the principall place, yet ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary rules are not by ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men altogether o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but in a calme they are preferred before the courage and deſperate reſolution, of the moſt vndanted hearts: ſo when any ſtate is moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed with garboyles, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke gouernours omit not the ready and neceſſarie windings and cranings about of the peoples inconſtant &amp; wether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke affections, to contrarie
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:12920:84"/>time-pleaſing points, nor any ſuch rules and ceremonious inſtructions, as experience &amp; that preſent ocaſion ſhal finde moſt behoofefull: but in a peaceable, tranquille, and well gouerned ſtate (ſuch as wee conuerſe in) (happie are the gouernours, but more happie the people that poſſeſſe by ſuch wiſe and woorthy gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours vnceſſant care and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancie, ſo great happines and proſperitie) wherein no tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent motions of ciuill &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke broiles daily ariſe, the well diſgeſted rules of expert ſtates-men may ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d one, that is to lanch into the deep of deep &amp; ſea-like affaires in ſtead, as wary card-cautions, to know how to beware of the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:12920:85"/>manifolde and diuerſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, and conflicts of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, that ſhal be laid in the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell waies of integritie and harmeleſſe innocencie, and ſuch infinite inconueniences as imprudence, temeritie, or improuidence, may expoſe a mans life and fortunes vnto.</p>
               <p>And therefore be not nicely obſtinate in yeeleding to this my ſo much deſired requeſts, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. you ſhall performe to me a moſt kinde office, and no waies (I will vndertake) wrong your ſelfe, and although that gould which is digged out of the earth by vs with greateſt trauel is beſt regarded; and benefits hardly obtained, are vſually beſt beloued; yet thinke you
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:12920:85"/>ſhal vnmyne your mindes gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den collections to a heart that can diſtinguiſh the qualitie of guifts, and the natures of the giuers. And be moſt aſſured, that your free &amp; vnforced ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſhall neuer paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their moſt valuable and weightie acceptance, from the Altar of my heart: ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that I ſhall not neede by any further ſecondings, and begging interpellations, to ſet <hi>Mindus</hi> his gates before the towne of your diſcharge &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formance I leaue you like a towne, as I hope conquered by the powerfull charge of this my rebeſieging ſolicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:86"/>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:12920:86"/>
               <head>An anſwere to the replication.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">X</seg>ENOPHANTVS, (right worthy ſir) cuſtomably vſed by certain mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which hee exerciſed and plaide vppon a Flute, to ſette ALEXANDER foorthward to battell.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:12920:87"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Xenophantus</hi> might haue bin ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an exquiſite muſitian, if he could by his skil haue drawn <hi>Alexander</hi> from war: for to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial affaires, he was naturally of himſelf inclined, and needed no prouoking incitements, to ſtirre his warlike ſpirit to battel, wher in he ſo much &amp; ſo inordinately delighted. Your perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue euer had as powerful operation in my breaſt, as euer either <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus</hi> or <hi>Ario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> his muſick had to delight &amp; draw the ſenſes of any mortal. But ſurely in this kinde, your importunate requeſts, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rauiſh &amp; inforce my will &amp; conſent, then like <hi>Xenophantus</hi> meaſures perſwade my affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For <hi>Alexander</hi> was neuer ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to march againſt his enemies, as I am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to put in battell arraye
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:12920:87"/>ſuch diſtracted precepts, as ſicknes, and ſorrowe thereof conceaued, ſhall be compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and prepoſitors of: you ſhould haue needed ſmal ſtore of coniurations in any other procurations. But howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, you muſt not be denied, &amp; your ſweete and delicate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions haue bene to me in all your requeſts, like CAIVS FVRIVS CRESINVS his field-inſtrumentes, powerfull, and vnreſiſtable bewitchings, and therefore I will make vſe of that politicke rule, <hi>Sapere eſt id ſponte amittere, quod tenere amplius non poteris,</hi> a woman were as good yeeld that to a man at firſt, which ſhe findes by loue tobe once conquered, and by <hi>Cupids</hi> batterie beaten down and ſubdued: &amp; I finding a weake heart, ſet againſte
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:12920:88"/>the moſt powerfull &amp; puiſſant forces of your vertuous loue, and moſt to be beloued ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues) will moſt chearfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect and erect my fainting and languiſhing ſpirit, with the comfortable conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your promiſes, &amp; hope and deſire to giue vnto your vndeniable requeſts, all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable and ſatiſfiing content and the rather for that I aſſuer my ſelfe, that your ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-ſhining and ſupporting fauour, ſhall not be wanting to my weake &amp; infirme ſupplies, as I ſhalbe inabled to diſgeſt and recouer them, to your ſight and vſe.</p>
               <p>And becauſe (to cut of all further ambages) all riuers are ſaide to flowe from the ſea, and thither to returne againe,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:12920:88"/>and all Actions to bee mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured out by the affects of the heart, which is like the fadom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and vnfoundeable ſea, to the plummets of any outward appearance, I will in the firſt place preſcribe you Sea-rules for the ſound of your heart &amp; affections, how farre you may flow ouer, and how much you muſt reſtraine your ſurging &amp; inundating appetites thereof, as the neceſſitie of ſpeciall occaſions &amp; occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:89"/>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:12920:89"/>
               <head>Concerning gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and particular truſts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et Therefore your heart bee generally affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Chymicall glaſſes, or poore mens chriſtmas Boxes are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; faſhioned: Let downe many mens hearts and ſecrets into the deepe bellyed Glaſſe of obſeruations, but let the mouth thereof bee narrowe
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:12920:90"/>and open but to a fewe, <hi>parcè deſumpta,</hi> vſe them pinchingly and ſparinglye, as Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vſe their ſecreteſt conuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances (not as Clownes their trumping alarums) as neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall extract &amp; wreſt them out from you, for ſome further eaſe or aduantage: vſe them as graue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellors ſmiles, not as rude Hobbinolds ger-laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who thinke they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer merry, except they caſt the houſe out of the Windowes with extreame ſecuritie, and forgetfulneſſe of all humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ceremonye of ciuilitie, as Vſurers, not as Prodigalles vſe their Purſes, Let your heart ſtand, concerning the drawinges and with-draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges of your truſtes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:12920:90"/>as your Cabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net is furniſhed with ſeuerall and cloſe drawers &amp; boxes.</p>
               <p>Your Cabonet hath a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall drawer belowe all the reſt, for your looſe &amp; idle papers, which is without any ſpeciall locke or Barre, onely the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall doore beeing opened, you may with eaſe and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labour drawe out and admitte ſuch general conceits as are curſorily to bee vſed.</p>
               <p>All the reſt of your Cabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net drawers are diſcreetly and with good iudgement diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed to particuler ſecrets, ſome to the receipt of your Iewels, ſome to one priuate and peculiar vſe, ſome to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all which are reſtrained from any others eye or viewe,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:12920:91"/>being with ſeuerall Keyes and wards barred &amp; debarred your beſt and moſte indeared friendes. In like manner faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on al your both priuate &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral demeanor &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>For your ordinary followers &amp; ſuiters, men of lower ſtate &amp; condition, let your heart bee free and open to them, by one generall Key of admittance, to the diſcretion of your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cariage, which without any intricatenes of ſtudy, will be apted and inabled by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral obſeruations to ſhape eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man an anſwere, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his propounded ends, deſires and deſertes. For mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of deeper conſequence, keepe a particular Key to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſeuerall deſignement, truſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ve
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:12920:91"/>and occaſion.</p>
               <p>Let not in any man of note and worthye eſtimate, (either for honourable place or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue qualitie) through your hearts ſecret cloſet, and particular drawer, which may concerne anothers (as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be reſpected) affaires or truſtye repoſements, nor anye to any priuate drawer of your heartes ſecrets, but with the right Key, that belongeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlye and eſſentiallye to his owne particulars. So ſhall you in the firſt place, gaine the hearts and vnderſtandings of moſte men of ſpeciall worth, note and reſpect.</p>
               <p>Secondly you ſhal ad to inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious mens labours &amp; painfull endeuours, continuall inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, and make them
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:12920:92"/>willing without iealouſie (iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie which burdens and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth free ſpirits and deepe reaches) to vnſeame and vnrip their expenſiue &amp; elaborated obſeruations, to your diſcreete and concealing apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Thirdly through this your diſcreete cariage, and concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling conueyance (which will ſpeedely be diſcouered in a gret ſtates-man) you ſhall breed and ingendor in the hearts of euery wiſe and approoued ſtatiſt, that conuerſeth with you, a wonderfull and vnremoouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conceit, of your high and admired wiſedome, which by a ſpreading fame, begets an intire reſpect and inducing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of worth, and an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:12920:92"/>of worth &amp; wiſedome muſt not, in a ſtates-ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be neglected, (eſpecially among men of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) and (though of lower fortunes, yet of deepe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning iudgements) for that being loſt, a ſtates-man ceaſſeth (euen as a father ceaſſeth after the death of his children, to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a father) to be reputed &amp; eſteemed for a graue and wel deſeruing ſtatiſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly and which is moſt in your ſelfe, and for your owne good to be reſpected, it will deriue to your iudgement an excellent method and order in all your ſeuerall cariages, and free you from ſuch inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and incombrances, as an inconſtant behauiour, vnſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, and an ordinary cuſtome
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:12920:93"/>of diſperſing and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many ſeuerall mens buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, coherences, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, freely opened to the hearts priuate reſeruation, will throwe any man, ſeriouſly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in diuerſe and deepe deſignes, into. For as in a library of many of the moſt exquiſite and profoundeſt treaties of plots &amp; conueyances of or belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to a ſtate, except euerie worke and plot concerning marchants affaires, euery ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall accident and negotiation of french occurrences, euery proiect of ſpaniſh, euery ſcope of embaſſages, and intercourſe of Barbarie buſines, and ſo of the reſt, both domeſticke and forraine occaſions, be not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically diſtinguiſhed, and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:12920:93"/>neatly delineated into their ſpeciall quincunces, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar places &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, (whereby vppon a triſe a man may finde by the caſt of his eye, whatſoeuer the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of preſent vſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments call for) breedes more incoragement to haue ſuch a library (though of the moſt excellent manuſcripts) then the benefit thereof can giue contentfull ſatiſfaction: ſo doth the conferences had with many wiſe &amp; expert men who haue laboriouſlie and profitably trauelled at home or abroad, in ſeuerall and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct courſes of ſtate-buſines, as alſo the particular ſecrets of your equals, attending neere about a Princes perſon,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:12920:94"/>offered to your hearts truſt (as in the court an eminent perſon for fauour or reſpect of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhal want no priuate prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and inſinuations of ſeruice, ſo long as his wiſedome and fortune ſupports that well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten grace and fauour) if your heart be not able to clap a ſpeciall key to euery ſeuerall mens diſcourſes and ſecrets (ſuch as carry no matter of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or diſtaſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princes beha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiours, courſes, or affects, (for with the concealing of ſuch ſecrets neuer let your heart participate) they wil bring, by a confuſed intermingling of one mans ſecrets with an others, a generall diſtruſt and hatred of all your followers and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and make your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:12920:94"/>vtterly vnapt, and vnca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to make particular vſe and profitable application, of ſuch concluſions and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as from time to time haue bene offered to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence by priuate notice and conference. For your thoughts wil be euermore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly diſpoſed and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, betwixt truſt, feare, and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and when vppon any ſtate accident, you ſhould be admitted to action or publique aduiſe, you will be caſt into ſtrange &amp; extrauagant doubts, how far the reuealed truſts of this Noble may preiudice, and open your ſlender and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant behauiour to another, and how far another mans conceit (by promiſe and the lawe of
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:12920:95"/>courtierſhip, to be lockt from all others eares) &amp; common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may taxe and iuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne your leuity and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neutralitye to a ſecond, and a ſecond giue taſt and rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to a third of your vneeuen and vnſquare and vnskilfull handling of your court-cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages: which can neuer ſuffer a ſtates-man to thriue or proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but ſets by degrees in ſhort time (time the diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of all mens hearts) a day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hourely curbe and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle vppon the mouth of al his ſayings and proceedings, and in continuance makes him of a free man and reſolute, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bond ſlaue, and in all occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of ſpeciall moment, to cry mumm, ſtanding rather like the ſuperficies, following
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:12920:95"/>the lines of other mens di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, then a rule &amp; mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall line, to draw all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ciphers and ſuperficies of a ſtate, after his prefigured and deciphered orders &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings.</p>
               <p>And as in your Cabonet you haue one ſpecial drawer, which hath a treble locke not to be pict open by the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningeſt Iugler: ſo let ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of your heart be vnpaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and inuiable to any truſt whatſoeuer. Admit neither fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nor brother, wife nor mother, friend nor familiar, to keepe the golden key of thoſe miſticall and deepely diſgeſted treaſures of your hearts inclination, or your lifes conuerſation, let them
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:12920:96"/>be as your life blood, reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vppon no occaſion, where it prickes, or where it tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, or where it ſettells, for you may haue ſome ſuch ſecret greefs, ſome ſuch ſecret delights, and ſome ſuch ſecret vnquenchable flames, either of honour or pleaſure, as may not with ſafty be made known or conueyed to the moſte ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creteſt truſt and diſcouery of any man liuing. So ſhall you make good in your owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident that Italian prouerb, <hi>La lingua del ſauio è ascoſta nel ſuo euore.</hi> The tongue of the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is hidden in his heart.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:96"/>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="precept">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:97"/>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:12920:97"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond Precept.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering of affections.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Verie man doth wonder at an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Sun or Moone, and gazeth at a bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Starre, but fewe men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to vnderſtand the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and exhalations of their owne affections &amp; eclipſes of either that he auenly inſtilled light of nature, infuſed into the ſoule of man; or the wilde eſtranginges and aberrations
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12920:98"/>from reaſon, apparelled &amp; inſtructed deuinely, many times and in many men, with the ſupernatural precepts and inſtructions of religion.</p>
               <p>Two reaſons may be yeelded why we too negligently paſſe ouer and ſuffer to growe to a head of daungerous and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous cuſtome, any vice or diſorder, Lord-like predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating or rather tyrant-like lording and trivmphing, in our naturall diſpoſitions and inclinations. The one a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and ouerweening deſire, we haue by nature, to pry into other mens faults, and ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſlip the ſight of our owne ſlimye &amp; defiling filth of foule enormities.</p>
               <p>The other, is a naturall feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12920:98"/>to rip vp Chirurgian-like with the inſtruments of ſeuerity, our hidden and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly putrifiing ſoares and corruptions, to the coare and bottome of them, and to make often &amp; priuye ſearch into the cloſet roomes and angles of our flattered and ouer-ſliked &amp; ſmoothed follies, raigning within vs.</p>
               <p>For dayly experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, that euery Comet or eſcape in an other mans di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, from the perfect and exact preſcript of humane ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie, or other cuſtomarye rites and ceremonies, is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at like a blazing ſtar, and aſwell the pure as the impure ſighted, are called out to gaze and behould with ſcorne and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12920:99"/>diſdainefull reproach, our friendes or Neighbours ſlips and falles, and are by vs (euen manye times, where there is greateſt profeſſion of kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and intyre familiaritie) expoſed to the attrectation of euery paſſengers ſcandalizing and detracting tongues, when as the Eclipſes of our owne moſte vnnaturall and fowleſt abuſes and miſdemeanours, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not with any patience abide the blinde-mans eyes to bee lifted vp againſt them.</p>
               <p>And therfore theſe two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may bee well ſaide to bee like HIPPOCRATES his twins vnſeperable; they kiſſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, &amp; nouriſh each other.</p>
               <p>For queſtionleſſe the reaſon why we ſo much delight like
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12920:99"/>fleſh flies, to conuerſe in the ſucke and contemplation of other mens errors, and like <hi>Noahs</hi> vngodly childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, to take ſuch pleaſure in diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the nakednes and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of other mens imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; weakeneſſes (be they either by naturall or religious combination and coniunction as neare to vs, as <hi>Noah</hi> was to his children) is, that wee ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome throwe open and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer our owne hidden &amp; lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vices, &amp; vicious humors, or looke back vpon the wallet of our ſeuerall tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; tranſmigrations from either reaſon or religion: for the due conſideration of a mans own follies, is a reſpectiue cauſe, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual motiue, to draw him to a ſober, diſcreet &amp; chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12920:100"/>conſideration, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of other mens di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions or relapſes.</p>
               <p>For then our Friendes or Neighbours liues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſations, for offences and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors comitted, could no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſing that forrowefull note of commemoration <hi>Infandum regina, iubes renouare dolorem,</hi> but our re-ecchoing accents of the like well noted, and in our ſelues, ſo often obſerued apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and proneneſſe to boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and more ouerdaring pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, would beare the dolefull dittie of this commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerating reply, <hi>haud ignara ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li miſeris ſuccurrere diſco;</hi> wee would bee readyer to poure oyle, and throwe ſugar vppon our friendes griefes concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12920:100"/>for anye fault or miſcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, then with Salt and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar rubbe the gauled &amp; green woundes of their penitent and much to be bemoaned afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: For by a daylye and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall conflict had with our ouermaſtering affections, and vntameable rebellions of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we ſhall finde more paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the heate of the like fiers vented to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion, and leſſe leaſure and ſcope, to ſcore vpon the dayly count-booke of our idle apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and wantonlye ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, the marks of other mens follies.</p>
               <p>Therefore, firſt like a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man, I aduiſe you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a ſerious and ſober conſideration with your ſelfe
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12920:101"/>and your priuateſt thoughts, and to diſcouer to the block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and beacon of your reaſon, and beſt diſcerning fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, what maine tops of aſſaulting and out-daring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of paſſion, out-braue your Capitols beſt ward, or what Serpent-like affections ly hidden in the graſſe of your all-pleaſing &amp; delighting hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moures, and hauing diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the one, &amp; vncouered the other, to imploy your beſt volley of reaſons ſhot, to blowe of the one, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow your daily and hourely endeauours, to kil and wound the other.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the ſecret and priuy booſome vices of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are moſt offenſiue, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12920:101"/>though leaſt ſeene, yet moſt vndermining enemies, you muſt redouble your endeauor, not with a wand to alapat, and ſtrike them onely as louers loath to hurt, ſo as like a ſnake they may growe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and gette greater ſtrength againe, but (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Italian prouerbe, <hi>Sel'albero ha fecca la radice, è Impoſsibile che poſſa hauer foglie verde.</hi> If the tree haue his roote dryed vppe, it cannot poſſibly ſhoote foorth greene leaues) to drye vppe the venemous iuice and roote-ſap of them, and to ſtrike them through the heade and very life ſtrings, that they may neuer knit againe to your
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12920:102"/>offence, leaſt like a Snake laide warme to your boſome, they ſting you with ſome deadlye and Irrecouerable inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, and by giuing life and warmeth to them, to denye to you all life of true and eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all liberty &amp; freedome, vtterly captiuating your ſenſes to their ſlauerie, and eternall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</p>
               <p>For as the Moone beeing loweſt of the Planets, dooth coueigh and tranſport their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration and force through her Orbe into all Elementall creatures, cauſing alteration and change of humors, times and ſeaſons, yea, perturbing and diſtempering mans body, the Ayre, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges vnder her Orbe:</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:12920:102"/>
               <p>So doe our affections, (being but the loweſt and miniſtring ſeruants to reaſon) vnmaſtered and not ſet by the Quartill or Oppoſite aſpect of true mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and diſcreete and well diſpoſing order and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, carrie and conueigh diſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urbance and diſtemperature through the Orbe of all the ſenſes, and leaues all a mans actions, ſubiect to ſuch altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and change, as breedeth nothing but either fierie and violent motions, or friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and phantaſticall inflati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>And that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more powerfully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due, by your daily conflict had with them, theſe ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome &amp; ſo oppoſing enemies
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12920:103"/>to reaſon and perfect iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you muſt vigilantly and exactly, laboure to detecte and finde out the meanes, that ſo often betray your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the ſubiection of your affections, and hauing diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them, preſently to diſcard them (as moſt tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and falſe Pyrates, to the flouriſhing wellfare and ſafety of your credit and eſtimation) be they neuer ſo deare or beloued of your nature, and bene neuer ſo long had in requeſt of you, for their olde acquaintance and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity.</p>
               <p>For elſe like priuate Poſterne doores, they will continually be ready to let into your heart ſuch theeues,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:12920:103"/>as in time will ſpoyle and rob you of all your richeſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of either ſpirituall or naturall guiftes and graces, and like <hi>Dalilahes</hi> flattering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements, depriue your minde of all her Sampſon-like locks of reſiſtance, and ſtrength, and power of iudgement and diſcretion.</p>
               <p>And by the way I hould it not amiſſe, that when your minde is loſt in your affections you may the ſpeedier meete with her againe, to point vnto you affections ſeates.</p>
               <p>Loue hath his proper place in liuer, which till it exceed, is an affection moſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but when it ſwels ouer the bancks of reaſon, it begets the name and title of vice, and is
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:12920:104"/>indorſed with additions of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, wantonnes, trechery.</p>
               <p>And ſo likewiſe Ioy which dwelleth in the ſpleene, if it exceede not, cheriſheth the heart, releeueth the blood, quickeneth all the ſenſitiue &amp; intellectual parts, to a prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and agilitie in any honeſt and vertuous function, but if it exceed and get the rule and dominion of reaſon, and true temperance, it begets the name of wretched and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſecurity, diſſolutenes, ſcurrility, inciuility, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Anger, which dwelleth in the gaule, the moſt noble and heroycall affection, that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the phraſe of the ſcripture, <hi>Be you angry, but ſinne
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12920:104"/>not</hi>) the fitting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt helpe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of publike gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the moſt ſenſibleſt and ſeuereſt corrector of vice, &amp; all vicious outrages, yet if it be ſuffered to exceede, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets the name of ouermuch haſtines, temerity, &amp; ſomtimes frantick madnes, according to that of the Poet, <hi>Irafuror bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis eſt.</hi> Feare is the childe of ſafety, according to that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>mater timidi nunquam plorat,</hi> The mother of a feareful man neuer weepeth, the forerunner of wiſedome, according to that of <hi>Salomon, Ante ruinam exaltatur ſpiritus,</hi> the ſpirit of a man is lifted vp before a fall: but the beginning of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is feare, the trueſt and faithfulleſt companion of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12920:105"/>thrift, but if it exceed, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets the name of weakenes, of womanniſh and harelike timidity, of irreſolution, and cowardly flegmatique ſloth and idlenes. Other groſſe and foule enormities, your bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding will not ſuffer you to be acquainted with, therefore like <hi>Licur gus</hi> I hold it fitter to be vnmentioned, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wiſe to be enlarged. Now forasmuch, as I right well haue tried, that nothing may auaile a politicke man more then to ſubdue &amp; maiſter theſe affects, nor any thing wil, being vnmaſtred, more anoy, diſturb and diſable a ciuil &amp; publique man, I am forced to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force this my admonition touching your affections, as you meane to proue a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12920:105"/>man. When therfore by a due &amp; impartiall examination and diſcouery, made of your moſt impotent (&amp; yet moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) imperfections, you ſhall finde your reaſon &amp; true light of iudgement, moſt ecclipſed by the ouerſhadowing power of any particular, either earthy aiery, or cholericke interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of appetite and humour, &amp; the wall of your defence by any of them, made weakeſt &amp; moſt ſubiect to daily inuaſion, there, I aduiſe you to watch &amp; ward, night &amp; day, and to ſtand continual centinel, with your guarding and defenſiue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of reaſon, for that <hi>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> in a priuate ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold be &amp; is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly tearmed but an odde conceited humour, admitted or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by a publike man makes odious &amp; inſupportable
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12920:106"/>ſuch actions as are therewith intermingled. And queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, no actions of a naturall man, much leſſe of one that profeſſeth himſelfe a morrall man, but leaſt of al, of one that propoundeth to atain to high &amp; eminent place of publique gouerment, can haue his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per demerit &amp; eſtimat of praiſe or warrant of ſecurity, that is glewed in with anye powerful paſſion, or ouerflowings of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection: for affections are noted by the philoſophers, to be but alienations of the minde, iudgement, and reaſon. And a minde alienated from iudgement and reaſon (the true and onely diſtinguiſhers of wiſe men and fooles, yea brutes &amp; mens actions) what
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12920:106"/>can it produce, perſwade, act, aduiſe, contriue or proſecute, voide of palpable and manua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errors? Infinite fogges, and groſſe miſtes of darkneſſe, are affections inſeparable and moſt adhering co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions; Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections vnbroken &amp; vnbackt are our enemies free paſſage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>windowes, by which they may ſhoote in all their Arrowes of malice, enuie, ſpleene, ſport ſcorne and deriſion.</p>
               <p>They are the generall fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners and praeparatiues of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie common mans woe and miſerie, but Politicians &amp; Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts particular halters of ruine and perdition.</p>
               <p>Therefore, as the Moone at any time being in coniunction with any of the Starres or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12920:107"/>in either of the 12. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations or ſignes, then doe aſtronomers ſay that the ſigne is in that part of the bodye, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which ſuch a conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Signe or Starre doth rule, at which time it is verie dange rous to make inciſion, or to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen any vain in any part of the bodye, but eſpeciallye in that part of the body, which is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned of ſuch a ſigne or ſtarr, wherewith the moone is then ioyned: ſo of your affections, and the particuler predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate paſſions of your nature, either of choler and anger or deſire &amp; concupiſcence (for I feare not anye other in you) if you intend to proceede to the managing of manye, or anye weighty cauſes, you muſt moſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12920:107"/>warily prouid &amp; moſt cautiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recollect your beſt ſtrength of vnderſtanding, by reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelfe from ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and dealing with ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iects in the execution of anye publique function, as by your former preſcribed obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you ſhall perceiue to ſtand in coniunction with any your preſent ouer-daring appetites and affections, and neuer to truſt and admitt your witte or will to bee actors on the ſtage of the worlds viewe, in anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen place, part or duetie, vntill that fit that ruleth be fullye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer paſt, &amp; alaied. Imitate heer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dolphins who (according to philoſophie at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of any tempeſt, (ſuch as doth ariſe from the bottome of the Sea) are troubled with certaine hott exhalations
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12920:108"/>and vapoures) mount vp to the top of the water, to ſeeke for coole refrigeration (which is the reaſon why Marriners ſay, that when your Dolphins appeare aboue water, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth ſome ſtorme or tempeſt to be nigh) ſo when you ſhall finde your ſelfe by any, either naturall or accidentall diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; heat of paſſion, ſubiect to any diſorderly motions and perturbations, lye not ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the heat of that paſſion: but get vp to the top of your witts, (before anye tempeſt ariſe) your beſt reaſons direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, from them to take water and ayre of compoſure, and (according to <hi>Licurgus</hi> his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, who commended them vines moſt, by the which
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12920:108"/>the ſweete fountaines of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ran co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually) to aſſwage the heat of any ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mour, that you ſhall obſerue moſt ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging &amp; ouer-ruling in your nature, with the fountain water of ſome contrary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <hi>Hoc amo, quod poſſum qualibet ire via:</hi> This is true po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to be able to make all a mans affections ſubiect and ſeruiceable to any propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aduantage.</p>
               <p>A true States-mans loue is, and ought to be tyed with a ſlip-knot, neuer knit with any of his heart-ſtrings.</p>
               <p>He muſt onely imbrace the vſe of mens vertues, and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſeruiceablenes, with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward graces, fauoures and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, proportionable to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12920:109"/>their deſerts, not ſingle out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny outward affectation to any worthe, nor laye open any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward breaſt-detection of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and intyre deuotion, to any ſpeciall qualitie. He vſeth the benefit of his friendes and followers, labours, giftes and endeuours, ſo long as they may be vſed vpon good terms thankfully &amp; reſpectiuely, but hee wil, nor may vaile bonnet to his honor, for the retaining any mens loues or labours: for to doe ſo, would argue a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſeeme to ſpring from a rankeneſſe of ſome vnſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed affection, which expoſeth a ſtateſ-man to much inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe a ſtateſ-mans hate is nothing, but a wiſe auerſion
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:12920:109"/>of fauour and grace, befitting ſome preſent aduantage, not a ſetled &amp; digeſted diſturbance of ſpleene &amp; choler, yea moſte of their wrongs receaued, are but referred to the braines moſt familiar counſell-confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, not to any deepe or ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ouercharging of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, for ſo they would mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply his wrongs.</p>
               <p>Firſt diſtract the iudgement when it ſhould be exerciſed in more proper and neceſſarie occaſions.</p>
               <p>Secondly being admitted to lye boyling about the hart like ruſt and canker, would fret and eate vp the mindes marrowe of trueſt and calmeſt compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:12920:110"/>
               <p>Thirdlye, being ſuffered to feſter about the heart, would bubble vp at one time or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch lunaticke aſperſions and words offenſiue, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him of ſuch readye &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie meanes of crying quittance for anye wrong ſuſtained, as ſhallowe conceites would, of their owne accord fal into, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that true politicke rule, <hi>profeſſa per dunt odia vindic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae locum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly open to the world ſuch an impotency, as neither policy, nor court-ſhip can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, for if a man wronged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre mutuall intercourſe of phraſe and familiaritie, he ſhall be counted and mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſaying nothing, that the breſt is vlcerate &amp; foule with
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12920:110"/>rancour, and in court men ſay, hee that profeſſeth to catch at euerie Flye, ſeekes but mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to choake himſelfe withall, an error flatlye forbidden by SALOMON himſelfe, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Politician <hi>fatuus ſtatim In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat iram, qui aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſapiens eſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulat iniuriam.</hi> The Foole kicketh as ſoone as another wincheth at him, and they which are ouer haſtie to kicke often, light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſharper ſpur. I haue dwelled the longer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this point, becauſe I know your tender and ſpringing yeares, ſhal meet ofteneſt with ſuch oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as vnbrideled affections will offer to your waryeſt obſeruation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="precept">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:111"/>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:12920:111"/>
               <head>The third precept.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hirdlye, if you deſire to attaine to this true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, fitting him that ſhall ſitt at the ſterne of the common-wealth, and ſo ſit as hee may ſtand faſt in all ſtormes, abandon from your conceite this deluding opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that to bee furniſhed and formallye prouided (either by the helpe of your owne
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:12920:112"/>induſtrie and ſtudye, or dayly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference with maſters of pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie liuing or defunct) to ſpeake and diſcourſe pleaſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plentifullye of buſineſſe and affaires, of manye ſeuerall nations, and to know <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vliſses</hi> like, the faſhions, habits and behauiours of Rome or Rhemes, as we commonly ſay, may make you wiſe enough to gouerne the chiefeſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creteſt deſignes of a ſtate. For this ouer-greedy deſire to bee acted vppon vulgar tongues, for excellencie in tongue, skil, and varietie of eloquence and booke diſcourſes, begets a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular pride in the heart, which is onelye delighted in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhowe of ſeeming wiſe, neuer ſuffers a man to attaine
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:12920:112"/>to the true and perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any deep or profound miſterie: or as we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye obſerue in proud wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that ſo their outward ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit be geeriſhlye and wantonly ſet out to the pleaſure of the worlds appearance, and their owne exceſſiue luſt, they care not how poorely and beggerly al things are furniſhed within the houſe, either for dyeticall or coſtly, &amp; rich ſupellecticke appendance; whereas on the contrarie, wary &amp; prouident wiſe Matrons, care not how homely (ſo correſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly) their outward abiliments fall out, ſo as the inward furniſhments of their purſſe and ſubſtantiall lyninges of their houſe and eſtates be richly and repleatly
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:12920:113"/>contentiue and comfortable to their priuate thoughts: So fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it with men that are cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away and puffed vp with an extraordinarie vaine glory of being accounted rich in time pleaſing, and vnprofitable titil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of liplabored eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or time-ſpending diſcourſes of ſtrange and forraigne acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; they little reſpect, not can through pride &amp; deſire of oſtentation, ſound the depth of any graue or weighty skill, or expres in any particuler inploi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, any profundity of iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, or true inſight in anye weightie and publique nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, only they attain to the parings &amp; excrement of ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learning, the pithe &amp; marrowe they leaue behinde for ſapient
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12920:113"/>and well taſting palates, and you ſhall neuer ſee any ſuch formaliſts (as moſt of them wil be very forward in that kinde) intermeddle with deepe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Statiſts, but you ſhal ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly haue them come houe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring down y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winde, &amp; ſtrooke dead to the ground, like ſome haggard and keſtrill broode, with the ſharpe talants of ſuch Ierfaulkon-like politicians wel watcht blowes and vnavoyda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counterbuffes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="precept">
               <pb facs="tcp:12920:114"/>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:12920:114"/>
               <head>The fourth precept.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ourthly caſt from your opinion, that throgh your owne wittie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes (for againſt this rocke, many great men &amp; highly eſteemed for their skil &amp; knowledge in policy, haue run) and certaine cunning motions and operations of your brain, you are able to turne about the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:12920:115"/>wheel of fortune &amp; all felicity, as it were with certaine skrues and machinations, to what point you pleaſe: for certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as I partly noted of the iudgement of the vnlette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſelfe-pleaſing politician, ſo may I affirme of the moſte edocte &amp; ripeſt courtier in the ſubtill skill of cunning contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances) that whoſoeuer is at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time ſo fowly abuſed by the deluſion of his ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of wiſedom, let him know that howſoeuer he may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine himſelfe to ſtand in a faire and goodly paſture of delightfull and Oxe-like ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, through ſome fewe good ſucceſſes had in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, he is then neereſt the ſlaughter, and inuironed with
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:12920:115"/>moſt fearefull gulfes and quicke-ſands; and although the ground on which he ſtands may ſeeme firme to his ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe iudgement, becauſe it ſhewes freſh and faire, yet he hath ſet his ſtand indeede but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a quagmire, couered ouer with graſſe (and that onely greene and high in ſhew, but not deepely rooted) which if he perſiſt long in, and wade with all his ſtrength, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he treads, the deeper he is like to ſinke.</p>
               <p>For this politicke guidings of things by rule and line of booke-cunning, are but like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall motionworks, if any one peece bee diſioynted with a greater reach, or through ſome negligence, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:12920:116"/>or ouerſights (as who can ſo liue in a Daedali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anlaborinth of cunning, but he ſhall be forced to make ſome in his life) all the ſtructure of his imaginarie Pollicies comes downe together, and throwes the engine Maiſter of the work, euen when he is got vp in his conceit, to the top of his promiſed felicitie, into the mire of all misfortune, or like an vnskilful alchimiſt, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by his ſtudye and reading found out many worthy &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent meanes and medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble receipts, puffed vppe with the pride therof, falles to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree further, the practiſing &amp; finding out the ſo much ſought-for <hi>Elixar,</hi> which his conceite and skil is not able to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:12920:116"/>apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nor digeſt, &amp; ſo after many moneths, yea yeares tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, coſt, and charges, fayling either in his due proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtinte, and moderation of fire, imbition, nutriment, concoction, and ſuch like, leaues to himſelfe and others, that ſtood in expectation of his producements, ſtupified to behould the ſame, a meere lump of droſſe, for their hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and longing deſires, or by too much ſpeed, negligence, or ouerſight in the leaſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, breakes aſunder his worke before it come to hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and thereby ſends ſuch a ſulfurous &amp; noiſome ſtinch into his braines, as makes him neuer able to recouer his perfect ſenſes againe: ſo theſe
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:12920:117"/>vnskilfull practiſers by booke and rule of all politicke foyles that depend as it were vppon their <hi>Puncto, reuerſo, ſtockado,</hi> and ſuch like obſeruations of cunning booke-policie, fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (that I may make no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther application heereof) of ſome out blunt and plaine downe thruſt offered them, ſtand ſtabbed at the heart, in their ſeuerall hopes, and leaue themſelues a publique ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of ſcorne and defamation to the view of the whole world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="precept">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:12920:117"/>
               <head>The fift precept.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Iftly, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue himſelfe to be immooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably fixed (for in this quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand likewiſe the greateſt Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars of the ſtate haue beene ſwallowed vp) in his religion, if he be touched with the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of any. For though it may not be denied, but that in many matters a wiſe States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath liberty to change his opinion, as reaſon
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:12920:118"/>&amp; the diſcretion of preſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, ſhall guide him, yet in ſuch actions and accidents as ſhall touch the triall of a good conſcience, in relinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the ſame, for any preſent aduantage, is not onely very dangerous, and ſildome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but it returnes in the iſſue much inconuenience, &amp; irrecouerable loſſe of honour and reputation; but by degrees depriues a man vtterly of his perfect iudgement and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing knowledge in affaires and buſines of the State. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauill</hi> therefore (whether men tearme him <hi>Hatcheuil,</hi> or not to be macht in euill, it bootes not) in this reſpect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades his ſchollers wiſely (in my poore conceit) either not
<pb facs="tcp:12920:118"/>at all to deuote himſelfe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny religion, or elſe neuer to forſake their conſcience; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be abſolutely good or abſolutely ill, not to hang in vncertaintie, ſometimes incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to good actions, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ill, as they beſt ſeeme to further their preſent vſe &amp; imployment.</p>
               <p>For he which is markt with Gods ſignet, and priuateſt ſtampe for his owne, by incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to euill motions &amp; looſe digeſtions (the lime-twigs of honour, ſafety, and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is drawne by degrees into deſperate attempts, which when he hath entred into, and waded chin-deepe therein, is ſuddainely recalled by a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpirit to a conſideration of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:12920:119"/>his folly, wherby it happeneth that plunged betwixt two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, he can neither get forward nor backward, and ſo become a ridiculous obloquie to his enemies, a confuſion to his friends &amp; followers, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſore &amp; vlcer to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily &amp; poſterity, whereas if he were abſolutely reſolued by wicked meanes to goe through all his purpoſes, hee ſhould finde no interruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his courſes, to countercheck his vngodly proceedings, whereby he might effect more with greater felicity &amp; admira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, then any man, partly reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious &amp; indifferently affected to pietie and godlines. This made the ancient Romanes <hi>Brutus, Caſsius, Decij,</hi> and many
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:12920:119"/>more of that ranke, to deſerue ſo well in the opinion of thoſe times for their fortitude and magnanimitie, ſhewed &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued in many deſperate &amp; dangerous attempts. For they being touched with no relliſh of religion, made fame and glory the chiefe ſcope, and ayme of all their aduentures, and ingagements, to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining whereof they reſolued their reaſon to feare nothing that could happen within the compaſſe of mortalitie.</p>
               <p>To this agrees all their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh poſitions and maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mees. <hi>Aut dignitatem retinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, aut vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cum dignitate amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus,</hi> and ſuch like, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeares, that they helde true valoure, and Magnanimitie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:12920:120"/>in auoyding of ſubiection, and that the quiet and patient tolleration of aduerſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, drawing vnder the yoak of obedience, and ſubſcribing to domination, rule, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, was baſenes, &amp; bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhnes, and therefore the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, and indeede (in the true ſenſe of reaſon) more bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh attempting of any thing might tend to their ſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed liberties, being reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by any lawe, power or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraintie, to proceede from a braue ſpirit, a high and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous reſolution, and not onely murdering of others, that ſtood in the way of their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes &amp; aſpiring hopes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue immortall praiſe &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but the cutting of the thrids
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:12920:120"/>of their owne liues, their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and poſterities, in matters that might carrie ſhewe of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique reformation, or preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their accounted honours or their Wiues and Childrens chaſtities, to be actions not only to be dignified, but to bee deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And queſtionleſſe, in theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and times, and in theſe parts, where religion moſt flouriſheth they who neuer had anye ſenſe or feeling of Religon, (whether they bend their mindes to the compaſsing of high and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters, in or belonging to a publik ſtate, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triuing any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary plot in their priuate affaires) they may with a nimb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler &amp; prompter dexteritie, paſſe through all their purpoſes, then they which are clogged and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with rules and reſtraints of religion.</p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:12920:121"/>
               <p>For as the profeſſion of piety, and religion, to a man through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excerciſed therein, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely bent to forſake any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or worldly profit, rather then to admit the leaſt diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or impeachment to the ſame, furniſheth him with a thouſand helping hands, in the profecution of any propounded imployments: So, to his purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and proiects, that profeſſing feligion, hath, or ſhall diſpute within the ſecret cloſet of his thoughts, this is proper to the furtherance of my particular, howſoeuer irreligious, treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, diſhoneſt, vnfaithfull, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and yet admits the good of his preferment and aduantage to high and greate places and preheminences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the good warrant of his conſcience, nothing is or
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:12920:121"/>can be imagined more interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or diameter like oppoſing, then religion. For ſuch a man ſhall finde, let his proiect ſeeme in the beginning neuer ſo cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, the meanes in his conceit neuer ſo cleere, a thouſand ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and vnexpected counter-maunds, that religion &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his vnſetled reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will caſt, as ſo many clogs &amp; fetters into the mid-way of his haſty-pac' de-intentions. For as a man that leapeth from a high banck, ouer a narrow pit or deep ditch, to folow ſome may game, by reaſon of his eaſie and ſpeedy deſcent (for <hi>Facilis deſcenſus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerni</hi>) is flatteringly pleaſed with his ſmooth &amp; currant paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, but conſidering not how he ſhall recouer the hold of his ſure feeting, and the firme and knowne ground of his
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:12920:122"/>ſecurity, is forced at his returnes either by venturing to fall into the midſt of the miry ditch; or to goe many miles about, or to continue as a man outed of his confines: ſo fareth it with them, who for the compaſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny priuate reſpect, leap ouer the knowne bounds &amp; pales of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Religion, whereby they haue bin directed in ther former courſes. For they behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in al their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, either like an army out of ranke and order, ſtill reſolued to ſome deſperate inroads, &amp; ſo be come like a ſhip without his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots and failes, fitted for confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and prepared to runne into the ditches &amp; ſhelues of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſters, or ſtriuing to go a neerer way, either to thrift, preferment or dignitie, being leapt from their owne wel knowne &amp; trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:12920:122"/>pathes of vpright dealing, to a ſelfe conceited courſe of cunning and irreligious pollicy, ſtand like me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thoſe trades and exerciſes they were trained vp in all their liues, for ſome new fangle deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and inuentions, a mazed, and to ſeeke in euerie particular, and ſo after much labour, vexation of ſpirit and anguiſh of minde, returne by weeping Croſſe to their former ſtandes; or if they reſt contented to runne on in their approued &amp; propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded determinations of follie, (which is the worſt degree of al) in the ende hauing outed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their meanes &amp; hopes, paſſe by their friends like a ſhip fallen into the hands of Pyrates, weather beaten and diſpoyled of all his braue array and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is as ruthful a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:12920:123"/>as the eie of man can behold. Therfore I wiſh him (vnworthy to aduiſe) that deſireth to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue his wiſedome, either in not failing in his attemp ts, or not falling by his attempts into any groſſe and palpable errour, neuer to diſpenſe with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in any matter of weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conſequence and momente, but to make that the touch-ſtone of all his proceedings, ſo ſhall he be ſure both to vndertake &amp; entertaine nothing, the iſſue wherof may prooue dangerous, and alſo to add like a ſtaide pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, a daily increaſe and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of iudgement, to his skill &amp; knowledge in waightie affaires and occurrences of the ſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="precept">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:12920:123"/>
               <head>The ſixt precept.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ixtly and laſtly, let your endeuour chiefly &amp; princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, be excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as may aduance the glory of Gods truth, and forward by all poſſible meanes, the peace, the quiet, and the proſperitie of the Common Wealthe,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:12920:124"/>For ſurely he that is ſo affected and reſolued to God &amp; his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries good, he may aſſure himſelf that hee is in a right way to the attaining of a ſound and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Iudgement in all weightie determinations, and the more this reſolution groweth vp in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, the greater increaſe and growth ſhall hee ſinde daylye in ſtate-learning and wiſdome, for the ſpirit of vnderſtanding, the ſpirit of Counſell, the ſpirit of knowledge, are inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panions of the feare of God and the loue of his name, neither ſhall wee finde farre from theſe companions a good eſtimation grace and fauour with all men, as well Prince and Peeres, as the better ſort of the commons. For that man winneth moſte inward credit and opinion of wiſdome, and moſte outward regarde and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:12920:124"/>honorable reſpect with all men, whoſe ſayings and doings carry moſt opinon of vertue, religion, &amp; honeſty among men; as if he ſhal ſpeak or promiſe any thing, men will not doubt of his truth, if hee doth any thing (whereof publike notice is taken) men wil applaude &amp; account it for right, and to a right and euen end: if he commaund any thing, men will moſt willinglye obey it; if hee giue counſell men wil reſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely imbrace and entertaine it, and haue euermore in high ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in all cauſes. But vaine are they who thinke this eſtimation to be compaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or if compaſſed to bee dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; permanent, which is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by palpable and groſſe flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, by diſſembling, or deceite, yea by any other meanes then by vertue in wiſdome, and wiſdom
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:12920:125"/>in vertue often ſhewed with good ſucceſſe, for al mens harts are kindled with admiration of vertue, and a ſupernall help and diuine aſſiſtance, yea the very wicked diſſemblers, &amp; cunnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt temporizers themſelues, hold ſuch men, who are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truly religious, &amp; religiouſly prudent and prouident for the common good &amp; ſafety, in great reuerence, and feare to diſpleaſe them, whereas they make no great reckoning of ſuch ſtatiſts, whome they know to liue by the like cunning &amp; deceit, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues doe, for cunning they know may be met withall by the like cunning, and ape-like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite may bee ouerthrowne, and caught by foxe-like crafte and ſubtiltie, but they knowe not what ſhooes to prouide for the feete of this religious
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:12920:125"/>ſtateſ-man, nor what cunning deuiſes they may hammer out of their forge of knauery, ſtrong enough to encounter with him. For hee goes on forward in a plaine, euen right way of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and fidelitie, neuer or ſildom but vpon great and vrgent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſities, digreſſing into any by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, of ſlie, craftie, vnder-mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Pollicies, ſo as if anye man ſtudies to ouerthrowe him by diueliſh plots, and circumuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hee tyres himſelfe in his owne deuiſes, and the more he buſieth himſelfe in enuious practiſes, the more he lymeth, like a bird in a Snare by ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, his owne witte, and yet meeteth not with him, becauſe he runs not vp &amp; down through briars &amp; lurking holes, like a fox or a wolfe, wher the gins &amp; nets are ſet, but keepeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> road high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:12920:126"/>of vpright dealing, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fixt his reſolution in the purchaſe &amp; increaſe of his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fauour, to vſe no indirect &amp; ſiniſter meanes, hath confined and circumſcribed himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of certaine faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful religious rules and propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded endes, from the which hee will not ſtart or ſtray, for either the loue of his own priuate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or pleaſure, or elſe for feare of purchaſing anye other ſubiectes diſpleaſure, wherby it commeth to paſſe, that as in warfare, when other freſh water Souldiers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anye ſudden and vnexpected skirmiſh, are to ſeeke of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice &amp; place, hee preſently claps to his ſtation and is prepared to all accidents: hee medleth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ambitious motions, to ouer-throwe his Prince, nor ſtealeth by indirect ſhewes and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:12920:126"/>pretenſes of publike good, the fauour of the people from him; his heart, againſt the falſe alaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſuch priuy thoughts and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, is euer ſet as a Tennis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal, which no ſooner receaueth but at the very ſame inſtant and moment of time returnes &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerberates the ball backe again, and if any looſe bent nouices (as it ſeldome happens) for they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeek out mud-walles, to faſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en their wicked plots vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtriue to racket the ſame, or the like motions, through the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure of his conceite, in a trice before any chace be made in the firme and faire Tennis-court of his conſenting will, he bandees them ouer the wall of his heart, ſo as they neuer returne or take further fixation. He profuſely ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oteth not his own, to wring and wreſt away other mens eſtates,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:12920:127"/>nor deuiſeth ouer-greedye taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and penalties to pinch the poore commons with all, hee is not heart ſicke nor head ſick, nor ſtomack ſick, for his adhabitants vinyards: he enuies nomans pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity &amp; honorable purchaſes of his princes fauours, he is not pragmatically ſcrupulous, nor too inquiſitiuely prying into other mens eſcapes and errors, ſuch as hurt not, or diſturbe the quiet of the ſtate, therby to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe himſelf hatred, but is ſorry when any garbage of foule and treaſonable actions is thrown in to the priuy cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the ſtates welfare, &amp; remooues the ſtinche &amp; poiſonus infection therof fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the princes perfo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the pure life blood of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth. He makes the lawes the boundes, by which hee limits all his actions, he truſteth not vpon former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:12920:127"/>thereby to preſume to run into any diſhonorable breache of Statute or his allegiance, hee liueth not voluptuouſly, nor effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minately, therby to giue, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mean men example to imitate the like vices, &amp; occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to baſe &amp; ignoble ſpirts, to vilipend and neglect him, &amp; that reuerent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ought to bee preſeruer in men of high place and dignitie: but to put into his equals hands, ſuch as are his aduerſaries, a fitt weapon to wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his credit, &amp; to diminiſh the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prince hath of his vertuous inclination, which being violated, there lies a free paſſage to infer by ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, iealouſies, informations, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefe may be imagined, vpon him.</p>
               <p>And this is that true wiſe ſtateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or <hi>Scipio</hi> of perfect pollicy
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12920:128"/>indued with this heuenly iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thus haue euer liued the worthy ſupporters of plenty and ſtate, making vertue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the baſes, wherupon they ſet the firme building of their worthes and honours, whereby they haue bene inabled to keepe betweene all rockye extreames, a middle channel of ſteeled tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and by an euen poyſing of all their actions to ſtand fixt and ſtable in the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts of enuie, &amp; long may they ſo liue, that fauour in this, or any ſtate, Religion and pietie, to the comfort of theirs, and true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions friends, and the confuſion of all malignant, diſcontented, and profane ſpirits. Much more I would haue added, but an vnv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall accident forced me abrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus to breake of.</p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:12920:128"/>
               <p>By the imitation of <hi>Silenus</hi> ther weare deuiſed to hang vp in the Galleries and cloſets of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, certain ſtrange pictures, ſo wrought and ſhut vp in prinate Tables, as if you viewed but the outward ſide of them, they ſette forth nothing but little ſmal il-fauoured miſhapen Images, but being vnfoulded, they repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome high and miſtical mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So in theſe preceptes, although you ſhal finde no pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures worthy the hanging vp in Princes or noblemens galleries, but rather at the firſt conceipt they may ſeeme idle, &amp; of ſmall worth and regard: yet if you can wiſely vnfold their ſeueral ſhut-vp, and incloſed leaues of ſtate-learning to your ſecret conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you ſhal finde ſome things
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:12920:129"/>in them worthy the hanging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your heart, as neceſſarie <hi>Mementoes</hi> to put you in minde of many vſeful obſeruations in ſtate buſineſſe: Vſe them not as your ſtudies, but as your watch at ſtudie, when your watch is out of time, you repaire to your key to winde vp the ſeuerall wards, that are therein amiſſe, and when your ſtudie touching State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires are out of time, and <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page,</hi> haue recourſ to this watch, &amp; in it happily you ſhal finde ſome key that may inable you to ſet all euen, &amp; in good temper &amp; order againe: What is herein wanting may be ſupplied, but neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to writing, for the next particular inſtructions of ſtate-buſines, which I muſt vnfolde to you, may not be admitted to any other boſome truſt. Farwell.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:12920:129"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Fol. 3. l. 7 reade literature for like nature f. 6. l. 21. voces for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces reade nor for not, fo. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> line. 17. read ther for the f. 8. l. 5. pleaſe for <hi>praiſe,</hi> fol. 11 l. 8 <hi>for as</hi> fol. 12. l. 11 reach for <hi>watch,</hi> l. 1. fo 13. <hi>and</hi> for ſtand, fol. 13. l. 21. reade not the 100. fol. 16 l 15 ſtates for <hi>state,</hi> fol. 16 l. 17 artizants for <hi>artiants.</hi> fol. 26 l. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fol: 29. line. 4 in reading <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> leane out the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. fo. 33. l 17 piſſe for <hi>piſh</hi> fo. 38. l, 14 and fo. 30 ſhould be 38. reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. thus not as it is printed fo 39. l 9 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thus, not as it is printed, reade prericraneum for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ericranion.</hi> fol 49 l 16 reade a duſſen of R. fol. 53 l 11 read &amp; the caſting, fol 61 l. 10, reade not &amp;, l. 13 <hi>eiuſd.</hi> fol. reade ther for the, l 15 eius fol. reade ſtaide for ſtate fo. 72. l. 7 ſweet bones leaue out the parentheſis. fol. 73. li. 6. reade to for ſo, line 4 <hi>eiuſd.</hi> fol, read not for oc, fol. 74. l 7 and for or, fol. 78. l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the for their line 12. eiuſd. fol reade paucos for paulcos fol. 89. l 13 and thoſe, leaue out thoſe, fol 90, l. 1. if for is, fo: 90. l, 20 ſeales for ſeates, fol, 97. l 5 &amp; 6. and for or fo 102 l 16 darknes for darnes fo 130 l 4 conſenting not with an 8 fol 132 l 9 Philodeſpotus, not lus fol. 123 l 4 preſerue for preſcribe, fo 149 l 8 and for leaſt, fo, 344 l 10 concernes not my perticular, fol, 147 li, 15 of your obs fol 161 l 10 reade diſcouragement for in couragement, fol 169 l 9 communitie for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly, with a parentheſis not at eares fo, 172 l 2, they for to deny fo 126 l 6 pyroters for pyrates fol 128 l 10 in the liuer fo, 129 l 18 leatcherie for treacherie, 130 fol &amp; li 2, ſuch as doth ariſe from the bottome of the ſea, read after vapours, ſo 137 &amp; l 21 22 23, reade for for or, fo, 147 l: 3, ſome for ſuch fo 149 l 9 themſelues for himſelfe, fo: 159 l 1 ſuggeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for digeſtions, fol 159 l 15 imployment for imployments, fol, 164 l 11 diſtraction for diſtruction fol, 165: l 9 but for pit or fol 165 l 15 read after welfare, that it is ſo neceſſarily ioyned with his place and office, to remooue folio, 146 lin 18, reade preſerued for preſeruer.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
